<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vievve of mans estate wherein the great mercie of God in mans free iustification by Christ, is very comfortably declared. By Andrewe Kingesmill. Diuided into chapters in such sorte as may best serue for the commoditie of the reader. Wherevnto is annexed a godly aduise giuen by the author touching mariage. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.</title>
            <author>Kingsmill, Andrew, 1538-1569.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843749</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04866)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 472:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vievve of mans estate wherein the great mercie of God in mans free iustification by Christ, is very comfortably declared. By Andrewe Kingesmill. Diuided into chapters in such sorte as may best serue for the commoditie of the reader. Wherevnto is annexed a godly aduise giuen by the author touching mariage. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.</title>
                  <author>Kingsmill, Andrew, 1538-1569.</author>
                  <author>Mills, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[184] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By H. Bynneman, for Lucas Harison and George Bishop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1574.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Edited by Francis Mills.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L M⁴.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf contains a printer's mark.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Marriage --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8505:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8505:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VIEWE OF mans eſtate, wherein <hi>the great mercie of God</hi> in mans free iuſtification <hi>by Chriſt, is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Andrewe Kingeſmill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diuided into Chapters in ſuch ſorte as may beſt ſerue for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of the Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherevnto is annexed a godly aduiſe giuen by the Author touching mariage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by H. Bynne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for Lucas Hariſon and George Bishop. Anno. 1574.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8505:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8505:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He authour hereof, being a very yong Gentleman, ſo applied the ſtudie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of the ciuill lavve in the Vniuerſitie of Oxford, that he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained as much knovvledge therin as any of his time, &amp; profeſſed the ſame in keeping of publike exerciſes vvith great commendation. Yet did he not forget (as many do) to ſeeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof: but ſo earneſtly trauelled to vnderſtand the myſteries of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he thought himſelf neuer vvell ſatiſfied in any thing touching the ſame, vntil he could by word and writing giue accompt of the truthe, which he conceiued. VVherefore he endeuored to commit to memorie the text of holy Scripture with ſuch dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in learning, and often repeating therof, that he could readily vvithout
<pb facs="tcp:8505:3"/>
boke reherſe in the greke tong Paules Epiſtles to the Rom. and Galat. S. Iohns firſt canonical epiſtle, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pſalmes &amp; chapters of the old &amp; newe Teſtament. Alſo he exerciſed himſelf by writing of ſundry matters, that he might growe in iudgement, readineſſe and aptneſſe to teach other if at any time God ſhoulde call him therevnto. VVherof this treatiſe yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſome proof, which he writ being about. 22. yeres of age: by which thou maiſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue, what fruit the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch of God in time might haue reaped of his towardnes, if it had pleaſed god in this vntovvarde vvorld to prolong his days. He eſtemed not ſo much the preferment and profit, whervnto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes he might eaſily haue attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by profeſsion of lawe, as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable aſſurance, and bleſſed hope of life eternall, which he might enioy by the truth of the Goſpell and the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Gods holy religion. Therfore
<pb facs="tcp:8505:3"/>
to further himſelfe herein, he ſought not only the exacte knowledge of the greke &amp; hebrewe tongs, but alſo for a time to liue in ſome one of the beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, where he might, both by the doctrine and diſcipline of the goſpel, be dayly confirmed in the true worſhipping of God, and well prepared to the miniſterie of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. So he ſetled himſelfe at Geneua, where he remained, being wel liked of the learned and godly, the ſpace of three yeres. From vvhence he remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to Lauſanna, where beeing too good for this corrupt vvorlde, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this mortall life in the moneth of September, Anno. 1569 vvhen he had liued about. 31. yeares: a Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix among Lawyers, a rare example of godlyneſſe amongſt gentlemen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:8505:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iohn. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>¶God ſo loued the worlde that he hath giuen his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten ſonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhoulde not periſhe, but haue euerlasting life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:4"/>
               <head>The firſt Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶That many ſeeke the kingdome of God, and that men are directed to the knowledge thereof on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the worde of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xiij. of Mathewe, Chryſte our Sauiour by diuerſe Parables ſetteth forth and preacheth vnto vs the euerlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and amongſt other vſeth theſe ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, ſaying: The kingdome of heauen is like vnto a treaſure hidde in the fielde, which when a man hath found, he hideth it, and for ioy therof departeth and ſelleth all that he hath, and buieth that fielde. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the kingdome of heauen is like to a merchant ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſéeketh good pearles, who hauing found a pearle of great price wente and ſolde all that he had, &amp; bought it. Now I thinke there is none in ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate a ſtate, or ſo farre fallen out wyth himſelfe, but that he is very fayne of the finding of ſuch a fielde as is here ſpoken of: neyther is there anye ſo vnhappie a merchant but that he would venter farre
<pb facs="tcp:8505:5"/>
ſo that he myght come to the purchaſe of ſo precious a pearle, as to haue parte in the inheritance of the kingdome of heauen to enioy the reſt of God, and to dwell on his holy hill: yea many will ſay, they wyll be glad to walk &amp; wander forth the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte compaſſe of the earth, ſo that they might at length track &amp; trie out the fielde where in lyeth hidden ſo great a treaſure: and all men will profeſſe this merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, not refuſing the paines to trauayle thrugh the whole ſeas, ſo that they might in the end aſſure themſelues to arriue at the heauenly hauen of the kingdome of God: and who is he which ſo farre ſetteth the body before the ſoule, that be he neuer ſo ryche, will not ſell all to purchaſe that glorious iewell of eternall ioy? But (a lamentable caſe) fewe there are of thoſe fayning folke that knowe the right waye whych ſhould leade them to that pleaſant place of eternall reſte: ſo that theyr que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions are ſuch and the like: Which is the waye? Where lyeth the pathe, that we may walke therein? ſo Chriſt talking of a redéemer and a Sauiour vnto the blind man:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9.</note> he thus queſtioneth: who is the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:5"/>
Lord that I may beléeue in him? So Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip ſtanding yet in that doubt ſayde vnto Chriſt: Maſter, ſhew vs the father.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.</note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concerning that queſtion Dauid the annointed of God ſpeaketh by experience: Thy word is a lanterne to my féete,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> and a light vnto my footeſteps. So Dauid founde the waye euen by the lightſome lanterne of Gods word: wherefore he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth often and earneſt requeſt that that light might ſhine ſtill before him: thus he ſayth: O that my wayes were directed to keepe thy ſtatutes: open myne eyes that I may ſée the wonders of thy lawe, make me vnderſtande the way of thy precepts, teach me O Lord the way of thy ſtatutes. Directe me in the path of thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Theſe were the light and the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, the féete and the footeſteps, the way and the path wherby Dauid was directed and conducted into the field which we are nowe to ſeeke: and euen that commoditie whereof Dauid proteſteth ſo generally that hée founde in the woorde of God, ſhall be proued true in ſpeciall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of thoſe, that ſhall diligentlye marke and wyth earneſt zeale ſeeke to
<pb facs="tcp:8505:6"/>
vnderſtand this ſhort ſentence ſpoken of our Sauiour, and written by S. Iohn for our learning, <hi>God ſo loued the world &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶How pleaſantly and playnly one texte of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſheweth the way to life eternall.</head>
               <p>THis is a floure conteyning in it ſuche pleaſant iuice, that who ſo like a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Bée, ſhoulde ſucke the ſame for his ſtore and learning, he ſhall ſay with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration as the Prophet doth: O Lorde how ſwéete are thy words to my mouth? Yea he ſhal find that they are far ſwéeter than the hony or the hony combe: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde in theſe wordes is that precious pearle to be found, I meane the promiſe, <hi>not to periſhe,</hi> héere is that ineſtimable treaſure hidden and cloſed vp, as in theſe wordes, <hi>but haue life euerlaſting:</hi> here is poynted out the fielde of fayth, where we haue to fetche that treaſure: héere is alſo a light ſette vp vnto vs, that we doe not wander in darkeneſſe, and ſo léeſe our way,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 24. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.</note> I meane Chriſt that bright blaſing ſtarre, the true light of the world: final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:8505:6"/>
here is as it were in a plot drawn out, the worke of oure redemption, and in a knot knit vp the whole myſterie of oure ſaluation: and in handling hereof, I thinke it good to vſe that meanes that thoſe do, which when they haue an hard knot giuen them to knit the like, ſtraight they vndoe the ſame, and ſo make it vp againe with leſſe adoe: you may ſay then here is a goodly warning, <hi>not to periſhe:</hi> a large promiſe, a ryche pearle, a worthy treaſure, <hi>to haue life euerlaſting:</hi> but the next queſtion is, howe we may obtayne thoſe promiſes? héere is an ordinarie meanes expreſſed, aunſwering that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>who ſo beleeueth in him.</hi> This is the fielde to walke in, the foote we muſte truſt to, euen the fielde and foote of fayth: But whom? in whom ſhall we beléeue? here can we not bee to ſéeke neyther. For Chryſte ſetteth vppe hymſelfe here as a marke for our faythe to ſhoote at: <hi>who ſo beleeueth in him.</hi> Why ſhoulde we beléeue in him? Here is anſwere to that alſo: bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is that Prophet ſent of God, the ſonne, the onely begotten ſonne of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, therefore ought our faithe to worke,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:7"/>
and reſt on him. What moued God to ſende that Ambaſſadour, not to ſpare his deare, his onely ſonne? that cauſe alſo is not omitted: <hi>God ſo loued the worlde &amp;c.</hi> it was his owne loue, his frée mercy that brought this to paſſe: nowe (I thinke) there are no more queſtions to be made, no more doubtes to be moued: For if all were ſayde and vnderſtoode, whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth theſe pointes, it were ſufficient to ſaue a ſoule, and to make a perfite man of God. For beleue thou in Chriſt, as ſent of God, as the ſonne of God, conſidering thorowly the loue of God by him decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then as truely as Chriſt is the truthe and may not lye, thou ſtandeſt in the ſtate of ſaluation, thou haſt founde the fielde, &amp; poſſeſſeſt that treaſure, <hi>not to periſh, but to haue life euerlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The thirde Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶That the especiall loue of God is the chiefe cauſe of mans ſaluation, and that to the right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof mans estate must be conſidered.</head>
               <p>THus the knot being vndone, let vs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally conſider the partes and péeces thereof, that the very bowels of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:8505:7"/>
being ſearched, there may a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte vnderſtanding grow thereof: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſte ſteppe, the firſte entrie, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the worke of oure ſaluation, is the loue of God: <hi>God ſo loued the worlde.</hi> And to conſider how this loue is declared towardes man, therein conſiſteth the whole ſumme of our redemption. And the firſt conſideration herein to be hadde, is this, as whoſe loue it is we ſpeake of, for it is no vaine or light loue of man, but an aſſured and ſtedfaſt loue, the loue of God:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Epist.</hi> 4.</note> who is (as S. Iohn ſaythe) loue it ſelfe. Then what loue it is that is here mentioned. For God declareth his loue towardes vs in diuers ſortes, and manye are the benefits of God towardes man, as that by him we liue, we moue, and haue our being, he ſatiſfieth the thirſtie ſoule,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.</note> and filleth the hungrye ſoule with good thinges: And the ſeruant of Abraham when he wente a wooing for Iſaac, tolde his tale vnto Laban the brother of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca in this wife:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 24.</note> I am Abrahams ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and the Lorde hath bleſſed my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wonderfully, that he is becom great: for he hath giuen him ſhéepe and Beeues,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:8"/>
and ſiluer and golde, and men ſeruantes and mayde ſeruantes, and Camels and aſſes. This was a bleſſing &amp; a great toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods loue, but there was a better bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; a greater loue, wherwith God em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced Abraham and his poſterity, &amp; that is it whereof S. Iohn ſpeaketh: <hi>God ſo loued the worlde. &amp;c.</hi> It is a ſpeciall loue that is héere meant, and it néedeth a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall conſideration. Therefore that we maye the better acknowledge the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in this behalfe, it ſhall not be from the purpoſe to remember oure firſt ſtate, howe God did then ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a louing Lorde towards vs: then to ſet before vs our fall, that we mighte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what we are, whome God ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, as S. Iohn here ſpeaketh of loue, that God ſhoulde ſende his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne to be a pledge of his loue: then howe the loue of God did worke and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in him: fynallye howe that loue might haue his full effecte in vs, by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that worthy Ambaſſadour Chryſte, which is (as S. Iohn ſaithe) <hi>by beleeuing in him.</hi> Theſe being treated, in whoſe hearts it ſhall happen to take roote, it wil
<pb facs="tcp:8505:8"/>
be a ſéede that ſhall ſpring to that floure that withereth not, and fruite that fadeth not, <hi>as to haue life euerlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶Howe the loue of God appeareth in the creation of the worlde, and in mans first eſtate.</head>
               <p>FIrſt therefore the loue of God did mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelouſly appear in our firſt creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea before our creation: he made all thinges for the benefite of man, and man for his owne glorie, he beſtowed ſixe dayes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor vpon man and his neceſſaries, as the booke of Geneſis reporteth: He layde the foundations of the earth, and ſtretched out the heauens like a curtaine, he gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the waters togyther, that the drye lande might appeare. This he did for the benefite of man, bringing all things into an vniformitie, that there myght be a place of habitation for man: but yet were not all things prouided neceſſarie for the maintenance of man, wherefore he ſtayd his creation vntill all ſuche things were prouided as his heauenly wiſdome thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght beſt to ſerue his turne, &amp; out of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:8505:9"/>
thrée his firſt creatures, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the waters, he drew out his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures neceſſarie for the vſe and preſeruation of man. To the earthe God ſayde: Let the earth budde forth the bud of the herbe that ſeedeth ſéede, &amp; the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trées bearing fruite according to his kinde: God ſaide that worde, and it came to paſſe, and God ſawe it was good, it was good forthe glorie of God principally, and it was good for the commoditie of man. Moreouer God let the earth bring forthe the liuing thing according to his kinde, cattell and that whiche créepeth, and the beaſt of the earth, according to his kinde: it was done, it was good in the ſight of God, and it was good for the profite of man: of the firmament God ſayde, lette there be lightes in the firmament of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to giue light vpon the earth: Then God made two great lightes, the greater light to rule the daye, and the leſſe lighte to rule the night, he made the ſtarres al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo and ſette them in the firmament of the heauen to ſhine vpon the earth: God ſaw that it was good, firſte for his owne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, then for the benefite of man. Of the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:9"/>
waters God created the great Whales &amp; euery thing liuing and mouing which the waters brought forth in abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their kinde, &amp; euery fethered foule according to his kinde, &amp; God ſaw al that he had made, and lo it was very good, and al theſe things were made, as good for the neceſſitie of man. God made theſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for man, yea &amp; he made them bliſſed for man: ſaying, bring forth fruite &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie. Now when God had thus prouided all things to mans hand, &amp; ſet them in ſo bliſſed eſtate, then came the courſe of our creation, then he ſaid let vs make man: &amp; how? after what forme? in what moulde was he caſt? In our Image (ſaith the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie) according to our owne likeneſſe, not as other his creatures, &amp; therfore that this high point of Gods loue, might with the déeper conſideration enter our harts, Moyſes repeateth it double. Thus God created man in his image, in the image of God created he him, neyther did he make him ſole and comfortleſſe, but male and female created he them: neither when he had made man, ſtraight he caſt him of, &amp; ſet him as it wer a graſing with other his
<pb facs="tcp:8505:10"/>
creatures, ſo taking no further care of him, but without long delay, he gaue him his heauenly bleſſing, he made him a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne, and a ruler ouer all other his creatures, and ſtreight gaue him poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them: God bleſſed them and ſayd, bring forth fruite and multiply and fil the earth, and ſubdue it, and rule ouer the fiſh of the ſea, and ouer the foule of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ouer euery beaſt that moueth on the earth. Now beholde the loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes man in his firſte creation, God viewed all the glorious workes of his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and they were all pleaſant in his ſight, but he did moſte glorie in man, as the perfection of all his workes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hée coulde not but delight in him, while he kepte himſelfe in that eſtate: man was nowe a bleſſed man when God had bleſſed him, and bleſſed euery thing about him, wherefore Dauid rauiſhed in manner with the conſideration hereof, burſteth out in vehemencie of ſpirite, and ſayth: what is man (O Lorde) that thou art mindfull of him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</note> or what is the ſonne of man that thou viſiteſt him? for thou haſt made him a little lower than God,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:10"/>
thou haſte crouned him with glorie and worſhip, thou makeſt him to haue domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer the workes of thy handes, thou haſt put all thinges vnder his féete, all ſhéepe and Oxen, yea, and the beaſtes of the field, the foules of the aire, and the fiſh of the Sea, and that which paſſeth through the pathes of the Seas: beſides all this, he made him a Prince of Paradiſe, and placed him in a garden of pleaſure, where he turned him on no ſide, but euery eye was full of the bleſſing and loue of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The fifth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶The fall of Adam, and his miſerable estate by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thereof.</head>
               <p>THus God loued the worlde euen in his firſt foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherin he ſhewed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde tokens of a fatherlye fauour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes man, but this was not that ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue here meante, there was yet no néede of that loue: let vs therefore nowe conſider the occaſion of this our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, why God ſhoulde ſo ſhewe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie towardes vs as is here mentioned: let vs ſearch the ſore, ſo ſhall the ſalue ſéeme
<pb facs="tcp:8505:11"/>
more precious. He that can not in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe finde what he is of himſelfe, let him loke vpon Adam, as the childe on the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the true image of vs all, ſo iuſtly valewing our ſelues, what we are whom God ſo loueth, we ſhall haue occaſion to ſet the greater price on that loue, and it may be as a ſpur vnto vs, ſtirring vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a further thankefulneſſe. Nowe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when God had ſo mercifully dealte with Adam, ſettling him in that place of pleaſure, giuing him ſuch libertie as theſe wordes do import:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalte eate freely of euery tree of the Garden:</hi> yet leaſte the pot might ſet vp himſelfe againſt the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, leaſt by preſumption man ſhoulde ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance and equall himſelfe with his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, it was the good pleaſure of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God to giue him this brydle to byte on, and to kepe down that ſtomacke which he foreſawe woulde ſhortly ſwell with pride, ſo to reſtraine his libertie, as in thoſe wordes is expreſſed. <hi>But as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the tree of knowledge of good and euill, thou ſhalte not eate of it, for whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalte dye the death.</hi> This was the holy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:8505:11"/>
of our heauenly father, whiche it had bene the parte of man willingly to haue obeyed, alwayes to haue obſerued, neuer to haue reſiſted: ſo might he haue kept his poſſeſſion in Paradiſe. For all the benefites which God had moſte plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully beſtowed vppon man, he deſired but this one thing, that is,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>obedience to his will.</hi> This was a ſacrifice wherewith he woulde be pleaſed: he hath alwayes cryed for obedience, euen from the firſte man hither vnto: but he could neuer get it at any mans handes, excepting Chriſte the righteous. For Adam how did he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe? what obedience ſhewed he? he ſtopped his eare at the voice of the liuing God his louing Lorde, who dealte ſo mercifully and liberally with him, it was forgotten whiche God ſayde, <hi>thou ſhalte dye,</hi> and that voyce of the ſerpent, <hi>ye ſhal not dye,</hi> howe ſoone did that enter the eare? For the man he gaue eare to the Woman, the Woman to the Serpent, they brake the commaundement, they eat of the excepted trée: ſo the blinde led the blinde, and they fel togither into the ditch, they became ſubiecte to the curſe of God,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:12"/>
who called them to accompt for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and gaue to euery one his ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral curſe: here is the point, here lieth the matter a bleeding: this is the olde ſore (as they ſay) bred in the bone, that will neuer be gotten out of the fleſhe, paſſing mans cunning to cure, without a ſpeciall reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die prouided of God. O Adam how wert thou bewitched? thou wert once in an highe and heauenly eſtate, but thou arte falne flat to the earthe: thou werte ſure in Paradiſe, but now thou art endaunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to become a firebrand of hell: it was ſwéete meat perchance thou taſtedſt, but thou ſhouldeſt haue remembred the ſowre ſauſe that followed. Coulde not theſe bleſſings and manifolde benefites, recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of thy creator, coole thy preſumptuous courage? coulde not the feare of falling into the contrarie plagues and calamities ſtay thy wilfull appetite? O howe didſt thou forget that threatning, <hi>thou ſhalt dye the death,</hi> that double deathe, the due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of thy ſinne? But thou ſhouldeſt haue bene obedient: obedience had bene the waye to haue kepte thee vpright, but nowe thou haſt receiued thy wages, the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:12"/>
wages for ſinne is death.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.</note> Whileſt thou keptſt thy ſelfe within the bounds which thy louing Lorde hadde appoynted for thée, then waſte thou an happie Adam: O thanke God for that: nowe arte thou vnhappie and in miſerie, thanke thy ſelfe, thy ſelfe will ſinne for that. Thou waſte once in the fauoure of God, he ſhewed hymſelfe a moſte fauourable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto thée, whileſt thou behauedſt thy ſelfe as an obedient childe: but nowe hath he iuſtly turned thée of. Thou waſt once the frée friende of God, but nowe art become the ſworne ſeruant of ſinne, and bondſlaue of Sathan: this is ſpoken as by the mouth of God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15.</note> Then are you my friendes, if you doe what I commaunde you: nowe therefore arte thou an enimie vnto God bycauſe thou haſt neglected his holy commaundement: whoſoeuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth ſinne, is the ſeruaunt of ſinne:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.</note> therefore arte thou Adam out of Gods ſeruice: he that ſinneth is of the Deuill: thou haſte ſinned Adam,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> therefore arte thou not of God. Thou didſt once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a bleſſing at Gods hande, thou didſt féele no part of paine, God cared altogy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:8505:13"/>
for thée, thou tookeſt no care for thy ſelfe, thou waſt warme without clothes, naked without ſhame, ſatiſfied without trauel, thy meat was put into thy mouth, God hadde ſo bleſſed euery thing for thée, that the earth, the herbes, the trées, the cattell, the foules, the fiſhe, they gaue thée their fruite and yelded their encreaſe of their owne accorde, in the meane while mighteſt thou take thy pleaſure in thy garden: but now thou haſte ſinned Adam, therefore muſt thou harden thy handes to labour, thou muſt ſet thy ſhoulders to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burthens, thou muſt buie thy breade dearely with the ſweate of thy face: this might haue bene foreſéene: hadſt thou not ſinned, thou néedeſt not haue ſweated: but there is no remedie that man may finde. Thou art ſicke Adam, thou art ſicke vnto deathe, thou haſt prouoked the wrath of God, thou haſt cauſed him to poure out his vengeance, and to open his cup of curſes. O beholde howe the wrath of God being once kindled, ouerrunneth the whole worlde, for the diſobedience of man: ſée what a flame riſeth of the burning ſparke of ſinne:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9.</note> As before in obedience man was
<pb facs="tcp:8505:13"/>
bleſſed, ſo in diſobedience, of the iuſtice of God muſte he néedes be curſed: harken therefore vnto the dreadfull iudgement and hard ſentence pronounced vpon diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience Adam, thus ſayth the Lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 3.</note> by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt eaten of the tree whiche I commaunded thée thou ſhouldeſt not eate of, <hi>Curſed is the earth for thy ſake, in ſorowe ſhalte thou eate of it, all the dayes of thy life, thornes alſo and thiſtles ſhall it bring forthe vnto thee, in the ſweate of thy face ſhalt thou eate breade, till thou returne to the earth, thou art duſt, and to duſt thou ſhalt returne againe.</hi> O lamentable fall, O pitifull caſe, wherin thou nowe ſtandeſt (Adam) ſo cladde and clogged with the intollerable burthen of ſinne, ſo ouerwhelmed with the bloudie floudes of Gods vengeance and curſes, ſo pitifully and plentifully poured out vpon thy heade, and beſides this he may no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen enioye his paradiſe, he is diſpoſſeſſed thereof, he is baniſhed, he is turned abrode into the wide worlde, whereas nowe he might not ſo much as come neare the trée of knowledge of good and euill, for the which he ventred ſo far, neyther might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer enioy any part of that libertie,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>as to eate of all other the trees and fruites of the garden,</hi> &amp; loſt alſo the fight of the trée of life. Theſe are the wages of ſinne payde as debte due vnto a ſinfull and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent man: Let vs therfore by this knowe our ſelues what we are: What is Adam? he is but duſt, he is hated of GOD, he is aſhamed of himſelfe, he is curſed, he is ſicke with ſinne, he is deade, he is twice deade, ſubiecte to mortalitie, and ſubiecte to eternall damnation. Crie out then (Adam) giue thy Children warning, that they maye knowe themſelues, tell them in what caſe thou ſtandeſt, and what an inheritance thou haſt purchaſed for them. Thus ſayth your father (O children of men) he that hath cares to heare, let him heare. I was once a man, a frée man, a bleſſed man, full of life as God had brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed into me, the light ſhining rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute me, the mercie of God embraſing me on euery ſide: if I behelde the earth, there was bleſſing for me, ingraued as it were in the herbs, the flowrs &amp; the fruits thereof, turning me to the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ther I ſawe the ſunne, the moone, the ſtars, in them was God to be ſéene a bleſſed God,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:14"/>
likewiſe in the waters there were innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable tokens of Gods tender mercie towards me: ſo far was I in the fauor of my creator, I might ſtand in his preſence enioying his ioyfull countenance, yea, he made me like vnto his own Image:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.</note> But alas wretch that I am, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor knew not my ſelf, forgot my duetie, &amp; became far vnlike to my God, not like to my ſelfe, but altogither like vnto a beaſt, yea, rather worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a beaſt, for behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dul ore he knoweth his owner,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.</note> &amp; the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Aſſe he knoweth his maſters crib: but I man, nay the ſhadowe of man, a very worm &amp; no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I could not bear the yoke of my creator, I would not herken vnto his voice, I denied him my ſeruice, I haue ſinned I haue ſinned, therfore I am wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily rewarded: I preſumed &amp; am therfore brought low: I aduanced my ſelf, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am throwne downe: I haue eaten without néed, &amp; therefore I am ſubiect to hunger, I pine away for deſire of the fruit of that pleaſant garden, I thirſte as the Harte after the waters of thoſe ſwéete ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning riuers, I am become of the ſonne of God the childe of wrath, I am cleane
<pb facs="tcp:8505:15"/>
altered, I haue loſt the light, I walke in darkneſſe, of a bleſſed creature I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a curſed caitife: Where may I reſt myſelfe? I haue ſinned, and my ſinne is euer before me, againſt thée alone, againſt thée (Lord) haue I ſinned: I dare not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, my ſelfe in thy preſence, I tremble at thy voyce, I am aſhamed of my ſelfe. Whither then may I flée? what ſtay may I finde? I ſinke in ſinne. O that ſting of death, howe it pierceth me. O death, O graue, yours is the victorie, and thou Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than mine enimie how ruefully thou roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt? thou ſtandeſt with open mouth rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to deuour me, &amp; I finde yet no defenſe: Thou ſubtill ſerpent that dreweſt me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this net, how thou ſpetteſt thy poyſon, howe buſie art thou about my héele? how faſte hangeſt thou? howe ſuckeſt thou my bloude? O that I coulde ſhake thée of, or that I might bruſe thy heade: And thou Eue, which ſhouldeſt be my comfort, thou haſt as muche néede of comfort thy ſelfe, thou ſhouldeſt haue comforted me, but thou haſt deceiued me, and thy ſelfe alſo, we are become a curſed couple, and with my creator I finde this comfort, <hi>thou ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:8505:15"/>
die the death:</hi> verily it had bene better for me neuer to haue bene made, than ſo to haue falne into the handes of the liuing God. This might be a true confeſſion of Adams follye, and the deſcription of his eſtate after his fall: wherein we haue to conſider what we are of our ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſte, euen as it were ſworne eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and at vtter defiance with God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſixt Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶That all Adams posteritie are ioyned with him in the ſame guiltineſſe of ſinne, and ſo ſtand in the ſame miſerable estate.</head>
               <p>NOw the matter ſtanding at this ſtay, if God did ſo ſtretch his mercie, as that he woulde voutſafe to take vs into his fauour againe, &amp; to make attonement with vs, if we maye perceiue him not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our frowardneſſe to receiue vs as his children, then if we did not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily eſtéeme that loue, we were worthy double damnation. But let euery man be thus minded that he ſtandeth in caſe like with Adam. Let euery one conſider his neceſſitie and ſearch his wounde, and ſée
<pb facs="tcp:8505:16"/>
what néede he hath of ſuche a medicine: for ſome peraduenture there be, hauing ſo little taſte of the truthe, that they will ſay: what tell ye me of Adam? what haue I to doe with him? Other not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering their owne infirmitie, in whome the inpoſthume of ſinne lyeth ſo hidden, that they will beare themſelues as whole and ſounde, whereas within like painted Sepulchers, they are full of corruption, hauing nothing in them to ſhewe when they ſhall come to be opened, but ruſtie and rotten bones, and ſuche ſayings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede from them as doe declare their hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe heartes puffed vp with painted hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and double diſſimulation: Theſe men will ſay I am not like Adam, or if I had bene in Adams caſe, I would haue looked better before I had made ſo raſhe a leape: But, O thou man, diſſemble not with God, iudge thy ſelfe leaſte thou be iudged of the Lorde: ſearche the bottome of thy conſcience, take thy glaſſe in thine hande: is it a true glaſſe? what then fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou there but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very face of Adam, be it neuer ſo well coloured? It is true, it is to true, euery one of vs are falne,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:16"/>
we haue ſinned euery mothers childe, as truely as we are the ſéede of ſinfull Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is but vaine to ſay this, <hi>if I had bene in Adams coate,</hi> for we haue each one of vs in our coates cloathed a ſinfull Adam: or to ſay, <hi>if I hadde bene in his caſe,</hi> for euery mans ſkinne is the caſe of a ſinner: Nay we maye not ſo ridde our handes, we can not waſhe our fingers ſo cleane but that pitche of ſinne will ſticke faſte what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer face be ſet on the mater. O thou man that yet knoweſt not thy ſelfe, that art ſo benummed of thy ſenſes, that thou féeleſt not the ſerpent whiche lyeth gnawing at thy héele, whiche ſléepeſt in a deade ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and féeleſt not the ſting of deathe faſt fired in thy fleſhe, whyche bréedeſt in thy breſte the conſuming worme of ſinne: awake out of thy ſlumber, ſtande vp and hearken to the cry of Eſdras in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation wyth the Aungell:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 7.</note> O Adam (ſaythe he) what haſte thou done? for in that thou haſte ſinned, thou arte not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len alone, but thy fall alſo redoundeth vnto vs that come of thée: and ſo ſaith the Apoſtle: that by one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8505:17"/>
went death ouer all men, for as much as al men haue ſinned: this floude of ſinne, it goeth with a higher ſtreame tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the floud of Noe, that went euen ouer the top of the Arke, for ſo ſaith S. Iohn, <hi>the whole world is ſet on wickedneſſe.</hi> Thus do they ſay of vs, and we can make no better of oure ſelues: we are loſt, euery one of vs haue gone aſtray, we haue loſt our ſelues in the wilde wood of worldly wickedneſſe, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that blinde guide our owne wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full appetite, Adam he gaue the firſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, and we brake not the araye: he brake the yce, and we are lept into the ditch: we are all hong on one hooke like fiſhe taken with the baite, for we haue taſted of the cup of ſhort ſwéete concupiſcence: and as Eſdras ſaith,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 8.</note> we and our fathers haue all one diſeaſe, meaning ſinne that ſhrewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſhepe of Gods paſture: we are al ſicke of ſinne, that is, the griefe that Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras complaineth of. <hi>Ieremie.</hi> 31. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue eaten a ſowre grape, and the childrens téeth are ſette on edge withall. This Prouerbe did the people vſe in the time of Ieremie, murmuring againſte God, as though they were puniſhed for
<pb facs="tcp:8505:17"/>
the offence of their fathers: But thus ſaith the Lord: euery one ſhall die for his owne iniquitie, euery man that eateth the ſoure grape, his téeth ſhall be ſet on edge. Now what father, what childe is it that hath not taſted of the ſowre grape of ſinne? Dauid maketh thy confeſſion: we haue ſinned, we haue done wickedly wyth oure fathers: recken al the children to the laſt, all the fathers to the firſte, who is it that hath not eaten with Adam? the Apple, that grape, it ſticketh yet in our teeth, we are all choked with the core of carnall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence: that ſubtil counſell of the Serpent which deceyued the firſt man, it will alſo deceiue the laſte, that venime hath infected the whole race, the whole broode of Adams birdes: Dauid he thus ſaythe, of no worſe man than himſelfe, I was borne in iniquitie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> and in ſinne hath my mother conceyued me: Beholde no ſooner conceiued in Eue, but as ſoone deceyued of the Serpent: and this hath God to lay againſt vs as he doth againſte the Iſraelites: Thy firſt father hath ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 43.</note> and thy teachers haue tranſgreſſed againſt me. Séeing then we haue taſted
<pb facs="tcp:8505:18"/>
one meate, ſeeing that we haue ſucked ſinne of the forbidden fruite, what maye we looke for but to be ſerued of the ſame ſauce, euen that bitter gall the dreadfull curſe of God <hi>to turne to duſte, and to dye the death:</hi> In this ſtate ſtande we, vnleſſe God take pitie on vs, we are falne, we lie flatte on our faces, we are become duſtie &amp; deadly, we can not helpe our ſelues, but as the byrd taken in the nette, we lie faſt fettered, our owne eyes not ſeruing vs to eſpie any way to winde out, we are not able to moue our féeble legs, nor to ſtretch forth our wearie handes, our ſoules are ſicke, our hearts are faint, we muſt néeds yéelde to our enimie, and be taken as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners of Satan that fierce Serpent and fierie Dragon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſeuenth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶That the ſinne wherewith God may charge euery one of vs can neyther be bidden by vs, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by blaming any other.</head>
               <p>NOwe by this we maye conſider our fall, that we are loſte without ſome ſpecial remedie, and that we haue no part
<pb facs="tcp:8505:18"/>
in Paradiſe, we are in darkeneſſe wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out light, ſick for ſinne, panting for breth, and bléeding to death. But yet before we deſpaire, let vs looke about vs, &amp; ſee whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we can eſpie any hooke to hang oure hope on, let vs conferre and take counſel with our father Adam what is to be done: if there appeare any ſtaffe to ſtay on lette vs there catch holde, if we haue any thing to ſay for our ſelues, it is good to ſpeak in time. What then ſhall we ſay? how ſhall we begin with God? let him that thinketh himſelf beſt ſpeak firſt: wil he ſay thus: I am righteous, I walke vprightly, I haue recouered my ſelfe with good workes: ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am not faln, either I haue deſerued to be reſtored againe? Such indeede was the ſaying of the Phariſie iuſtifying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 18.</note> ſo he layde out before God his fardle of faſtings, his ruſtie packe of almes and tithes: but howe ſped he? the nearer the Churche he made himſelfe to be, the further he was from GOD, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted home righteous in his owne eyes, but ſo muche the more vnryghteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore GOD. O playe not the Phariſies, forget not your ſelues whoſe children you
<pb facs="tcp:8505:19"/>
are, what elſe but the childe of perdition, O earth, earth, that thou ſhouldſt make ſo much of thy ſelfe. Nay this is not the way to recouer the loſt Paradiſe: this was that fooles Paradiſe whereinto the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians were brought, and wherefore S. Paule rebuketh them: O ye fooliſhe Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians, who hath bewitched you?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.</note> are ye fooliſh (ſaith he) to ſéeke your perfection in your fleſhe? Take héede then. S. Paule counteth thee but for a foole, if thou go that way to worke, as to ſaye myne owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts ſhall rayſe me vp from my fall: no it will be but a vaine bragge in thée, and the encreaſe of thy ſinne, to ſay, I haue no ſinne,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.</note> that were but to proue thy ſelfe a lier: for if we ſaye we haue no ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues, and the truth is not in vs, nay, in ſo ſaying we make God a lyer, ſo farre as lyeth in vs: this therefore is but a ſtolne feather, belonging to a better bird, it is the armes of our heauenly king Chriſt, it is his enſigne wherewith he tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umpheth ouer his enimies to ſaye this: <hi>who of you is able to reproue me of anye ſinne?</hi> let vs not robbe Chriſte of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, let vs not make Gods of our ſelues:
<pb facs="tcp:8505:19"/>
for who is good but God? To ſay that we are guiltleſſe before the iudgement ſeat of God, in that we ſhall haue a thouſande witneſſes againſt vs, euen our own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience crying and conuincing vs: it were a better waye to confeſſe our ſelues ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for that waye there may be ſome hope: for if we acknowledge our ſinnes, God is mercifull to forgiue vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.</note> and to clenſe vs from al vnrighteouſneſſe: This waye did the holyeſt of all take: for what ſayth Dauid that choſen of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> he cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>againſte thee, againſte thee onely haue I ſinned, and my ſinne is euer before me:</hi> this was the confeſſion of the father, and his wiſe ſonne Salomon whom God had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſuch giftes, what hath he to ſay but guiltie?<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 9.</note> wherfore he maketh his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and as it were aforehande beſpeaketh the mercy of God for him and his people, for he foreſawe (as he ſayth) that there is no man which ſinneth not: and he maketh this queſtion:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prouer.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>who can ſaye I haue made myne heart cleane, I am cleane from ſinne?</hi> And Iob a iuſt man (as the markette of mans iuſtice goeth) he ſaythe vnto God holding vp his hand: I haue ſinned, what
<pb facs="tcp:8505:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhal I doe vnto thée?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.</note> And Paule the elect veſſell, doth not he alſo ſay guiltie, when he proteſteth thus of himſelfe: I knowe that in me,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note> that is, in my fleſh there dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no good thing: nay he felt the burthen of ſinne ſo heauie on his back, that it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him to crie with a great grone and déepe ſigh: Oh wretche that I am who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death. And that holy Apoſtle Peter what ſayde he but guiltie, when he ſayd vnto our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, departe from me (O Lorde) I am a ſinfull man. Let vs therefore followe the wiſe counſel of the wiſe ſonne of Syrach. My ſonne (ſayth he) iuſtifie not thy ſelfe before the Lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 7.</note> for he knoweth thyne heart: This accompt therefore muſt we make of our ſelues: we are bare Adams, and naked Eues, we haue nothing to hide our ſinnes, but the more we ſéeke to cloake them, the more they doe appeare, our own works they be but figge leaues, they will not hide our nakedneſſe, we ſhall be aſhamed of them, and will be faine to hide our heads from the preſence of the Lorde, when the coole of the day co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that he wil call vs to accompt. But
<pb facs="tcp:8505:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
why do I compare them to figge leaues? the Prophete hath made a meeter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of them: what is our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe like vnto? it is almoſt a ſhame to ſpeake of them as they deſerue: they are (ſayth he) like vnto a cloth beſpotted with the flowers of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O ſhameleſſe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites that can preſent the moſte holy God, with the ſhamefull cloutes and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ragges of their owne righteouſneſſe, and offer that a price of their redemption. Hath not God then left a lawe of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe by the whych we ſhall be iudged? Yea verily. But who will ſtande to the triall thereof that he hath kept that law? he that thinketh that iuſtification co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth this waye, lette him harken a little to the doctrine of S. Paule.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.</note> By the lawe (ſaythe he) commeth the knowledge of ſinne, that is, it proueth vs guiltie, it conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vs of vnrighteouſneſſe: and there is the office of the lawe: but concerning our iuſtification, we knowe (ſaythe he) that what ſoeuer the lawe ſaythe, it ſayth it to them which are vnder the lawe, that euery mouth may be ſtopped, and all the worlde founde culpable before GOD.
<pb facs="tcp:8505:21"/>
And this is his concluſion: therefore by the workes of the lawe ſhall no fleſhe be iuſtifyed. Nay let vs not take this waye, let vs rather craue a pardon than pleade the law: for that we ſee is a bone that cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs all: if we ſtande vpon the plea, we are ſure to be caſte in the great debte of ſinne, and after to be throwne in that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of darkeneſſe, neuer to be let looſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, no not til we haue payde the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing. Yet then we ſlide, we fall, here is no holde to be had, no reſte to be founde: whiche way then ſhall we nowe turne vs? Shal we ſéeke excuſes to cloake our offences? Shall we ſay this man or that man prouoked me to wickedneſſe? had not this cauſe bene, I had not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed: neyther will this cloake ſerue vs, it is not able to kéepe off the ſmoking raine of Gods wrathe, which is poured downe out of heauen vpon all vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. This way was fyrſt of al ſayed, but it would not preuayle with God: for when God called Adam to reckening and ſayd, why haſt thou eaten of the tree whereof I commaunded thée that thou ſhouldſt not eate? then did Adam put it
<pb facs="tcp:8505:21"/>
ouer to Eue and ſo ſayde, the woman whiche thou gaueſt to me, ſhe brought of the trée and I did eate: then God called the woman, ſaying, why haſt thou done this, and ſhe layde the blame vpon the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, hauing no more to ſay but this: The Serpent beguiled me and I did eate. But God helde not Adam excuſed by Eue, nor Eue by the Serpente, euery one of them beareth his iniquitie, and they drinke all of one cup, that is, of the curſe of God: ſo he that giueth euill counſell, ſhal haue the rewarde of euill, and he that followeth euill counſell, bycauſe he hath ſinned, he muſte be payde with the wages of ſinne: here then are we as far to ſéeke as at the firſte,<note place="margin">Without Christe is nought but deſperation.</note> here then are we as farre out of the way as before, here is no ſure ground for vs to ſtand on, yet that ſting of death ſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as déepe in vs as euer it did.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>The eight Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶The diſtreſſe and dispaire of man, in the viewe of his owne wickedneſse.</head>
               <p>HOwe then? is there no remedie to be founde? muſt we néedes lie ſtil ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:8505:22"/>
in the greace of our own fleſhly wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe? is there none to delyuer vs from this body of death? if it be ſo, then ſucke on Serpent, then death take thy pleaſure, then craue thy righte: graue open thy mouth: Hell ſwallowe vp thy portion: for thou God haſte forſaken vs, thou haſt yéelded vp all thy right: whyther ſhall we flée then? where may we finde reſt for our ſoules? Thy face (thou mightie one) is alwayes againſt vs: we ſweate, we burne, we frie with the furie of wrath, all places are to hote for man to reſte on, ſo is thine indignation kindled. If I ſaye I haue done iuſtly, then thou reproueſt me as a lyer:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.</note> if I haue ſinned then thou wilt ſtreightly looke vnto me, and wilte not holde me guiltleſſe of mine iniquitie, and ſéeing thou markeſt iniquitie ſtraightly, who ſhall abide it?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 10.</note> wherefore then hath thine handes faſhioned me? O that I had periſhed in my conception and that none eye had ſéene me, and that I were as I had not bene, that my graue had bene my mother: beholde I goe and ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, euen to the lande of darkeneſſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a lande I ſaye darke as darkeneſſe it
<pb facs="tcp:8505:22"/>
ſelfe, into the ſhadowe of deathe, where is no order, but the light is there as dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, my dayes are as the ſmoke, and my life as the ſhadowe. O ye wormes I am your foode, O corruption thou art my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, O death thou art my mother, out of thee was I taken, and into thée I return, to thée I bequeath that whyche I hadde from thée, this lumpe of earthe, this maſſe of fleſhe. To whome ſhall I betake my ſpirite? I maye not long poſſeſſe it my ſelfe, ſéeing thou wilte not haue it <hi>(thou holy one)</hi> I muſte néedes yéelde it vp as a praye vnto myne enimie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>The ninth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶That Chryste from the beginning hath bene, is, and ſhall be the only ſtaye and comforte of all ſortes of men.</head>
               <p>BVt thou ſonne of man ſtaye thée a whyle in pacience, doe not ſo gyue ouer thy ſoule, as to ſaye thy ſinne is greater than it may be forgiuen: humble thy ſelfe, acknowledge thy rebellion, but deſpaire not, caſt not thy ſelfe headlong into Hell: is there no remedie to be found on earth? then lifte vp thyne eyes to heauen: there
<pb facs="tcp:8505:23"/>
is a comfort, there is a comfort co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, there is a ſauing healthe in hande: thy wounde is great indeede, but there is a ſtrong medicine a tempering: thy fall was grieuous, but thy ryſing vp ſhall be as wonderfull: many and mightie are thine enimies, but there is one that ſhall fight for thée, whoſe name is the Lorde of Hoſtes, and he ſhall ſubdue all power. Beholde thy creator hath not vtterly caſt thée off, thou haſt found fauor in his ſight. S. Iohn ſaith, God loueth the world, yea, ſuche ſtore of mercie there is with God, that although we were his enimies, yet he is become our God againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 8.</note> and wyll ſtand an enimie againſt our enimies, and although he ſeeth that the imagination of mans heart is euill euen from his youth, yet he doth not vtterly caſt vs off: Goe to then Lorde we beſéech thée, we haue ſéene thy iudgements how terrible they are, we are full fedde with the gall of thy bitter vengeance, now if it be thy good pleaſure, turne thy face from our ſinnes, and blot out our offences, create in vs a new hart, renew a right ſpirit in our bowels, ſhewe thy ſelfe once againe a mercyfull God,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
we knowe we are not worthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy children, we haue ſinned againſte heauen and againſt earth, they bare part of our curſe: againſte thée, againſte thée haue we ſinned: but if it be thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, turne thy louing countenaunce to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs. Surely there is mercie wyth God, he hath heard the gronings and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of his people, he is moued wyth compaſſion and pitie towardes vs: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde we that were ſhattered in pieces, lying ſtill in the ſounde of ſinne and buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp in death, the Lorde of his infinite goodneſſe, goth about togather vs vp and to ſet vs vpright agayne, he intendeth to caſt Adam in a newe mould, and to make him a newe creature, not of earth earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but of heauen heauenly. For there is a Lambe a killing, whoſe bloud ſhall waſhe awaye our ſinnes, there is a ſtone fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, it ſhall be layde in Sion, it ſhal fall vpon our enimie, it ſhal grinde his heade and cruſhe it in pieces, we are but héele hurted, but he ſhall be wounded on the head. And it ſhall be thine owne childe (Adam) thyne owne ſéede (Eue) that ſhall thus ſubdue the Serpent. So good and
<pb facs="tcp:8505:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
gracious is the Lorde, he promiſeth a vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, his owne mouth hath ſpoken it, and wyth his mightie hande hath he brought it to paſſe: for God ſo loueth the worlde that he hath ſente: what hath he ſente? euen that ſauing ſéede, that innocent Lambe prouided from the beginning, he hath ſent his onely begotten ſonne bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him that pearle, <hi>not to periſhe,</hi> with that heauenly treaſure, <hi>to haue lyfe euerlaſting:</hi> héere then maye we caſte an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, all other remedies failing vs, this is it we muſte truſt vnto, this is the ſure pledge of Gods fauor towardes vs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this comforte we had bene altogither comfortleſſe, but nowe is our ioy full and plenteous. This is that ioyfull tydings ſent from heauen, brought by the Angell, belonging to all, as well as to thoſe ioyful ſhepherdes:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 2.</note> be not afrayd (ſaith the angel) for beholde I bring you tidings of greate ioy, that ſhall be to all the people, <hi>that vnto you this day is borne a Sauiour in the citie of Dauid, which is Chriſte.</hi> O glorious daye, wherein ſhineth ſuche a ſunne, the verye ſun of God, the bright ſunne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: in that day ſo bright were the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
<pb facs="tcp:8505:24"/>
of the ſunne, that they ſhyned eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the dim eyes of Abraham:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.</note> this was the glorious day which he ſaw with ſuch ioy. Nowe by this is God truely become the God of Abraham, Iſaack, and Iacob: here is the performance of the heauenly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and bleſſed bargaine made for him &amp; vs all betwixt Abraham and his God: for when it might ſéeme a hope againſt hope, that aged Abraham ſhould haue any ſuche ſéede, &amp; the Lorde knew that Sara would laugh and wonder at his worde, yet the Lorde of his loue wherewith he loued the worlde, eſtabliſhed his couenaunt wyth them, that in them ſholude all nations be bleſſed, (yea, we of England &amp; Irelande, haue our parte in this bleſſing) and of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Kings alſo ſhould come. And to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme vs in opinion that this is the very true promiſed ſeede by the whiche Abraham ſhould become a bleſſed father, and we his happie Children: and by the which Adam ſhould ſubdue the Serpent, S. Paule pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto vs arguing of the forme of the promiſe, he ſayth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>not to the ſeedes (as ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of many) but, and to thy ſeede, as of one,</hi> as thoughe he hadde ſayde: of all the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:25"/>
Kings comming of Sara, yet was there but one by whome we ſhall obtaine the kingdome of heauen, of all the ſeede of Abraham whyche was innumerable as the ſtarres of the heauen, and the ſande of the Sea ſhore, yet was there but one ſéede whyche brought this bleſſing with it, and that was as he there ſayth, <hi>onely Chryſte,</hi> and as S. Iohn here ſpeaketh, <hi>the onely begotten ſonne of God:</hi> for it was not that earthly Iſaack, that fleſhely ſonne of Sara: but it is this heauenly Iſaack, the onely begotten ſonne of God, that bringeth his bleſſing on his backe, neyther was it that Iacob the begotten of Iſaack, but the onely begotten of God in whome the promiſe was performed: this is that wiſe warie Iacob, that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planteth and vndermineth all enuious Eſaus: this is the mightie and ſturdie I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſraell, that ſubdueth all powers, to whom al knées (be they neuer ſo ſtiffe) ſhal crouch here beneath and aboue in earth, in hell, and in heauen: this is the very ſéede out of which ſpringeth all bleſſing, all that are bleſſed among the begotten of men, it is by this begotten of God, this ſeede bleſſeth
<pb facs="tcp:8505:25"/>
both the begetting and begotten, the ſonne and the father, the firſt as <hi>Alpha,</hi> and the laſte as <hi>Omega:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alpha. Omega.</note> without this heauenly Iacob, had that bene but a deteſted Eſau, and not a beloued Iacob: without this Iſaack, had that other bene in worſe caſe than wilde Iſmael, and in this Iſaack ſtoode the chiefe ioy of Abraham, yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Abraham was, this Iſaack was: for but in reſpecte of him had bleſſed Shem bene an accurſed Ham: it is written that Noah fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d grace in the ſight of the Lord:<note place="margin">Gene. 6.</note> had it not bene for this gracious Lord, he had not founde ſuche grace, for it was the hope of this grace giuen by Chryſte that bore the Arke, and ſaued him from thoſe roaring floudes. And this Iſaack ſtoode by Abell ſhadowing him with his bleſſing, while Caine was curſed: and this is the ſelfe ſeede that ſaueth Adam from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. And that bleſſed among women the mother of our Sauioure, wherein ſtoode hir bleſſedneſſe but in that the Angel ſaid: Thou haſt found fauor with God, for loe, thou ſhalte conceiue in thy womb &amp; beare a ſonne, and ſhalt cal his name Ieſus:<note place="margin">Luke. 1.</note> and ſhe of hir ſelfe: from henceforth ſhall all
<pb facs="tcp:8505:26"/>
nations call me bleſſed. From that tyme when God had ſo ſhewed his fauour, as that ſhe was ouerſhadowed by the power of the higheſt, and had conceiued that fruit of the wombe, then from that time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſhe bleſſed, and not ſhe onely, but all thoſe nations calling hir bliſſed haue part with hir in the bliſſed ſéede, in the concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fruite Ieſus. This therefore is the loue, wherewith God ſo loueth vs, that he ſending his onely begotten ſonne, his dearely beloued Chryſte, we ſtand in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie to become the bleſſed ſonnes of bleſſed Abraham: let vs therefore the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with our father reioyce in this daye, whereof the Aungell ſpeaketh, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Lorde himſelfe ſayth: Thou art my ſonne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note> this daye haue I begotten thee: This day was ſuch, as many Kings and Prophets deſired to ſée, yea happy were they that were ſo happie as to hope for this day: for all the bleſſed among the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers reſted in this hope? This was the comfort of Iacobs féeble ſpirite nowe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue, for thus he gloryed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſon Ioſeph viſiting him in Egypt in his ſickneſſe, and to him was it ioyfull
<pb facs="tcp:8505:26"/>
tydings to hear that ſaying at his fathers mouth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 48.</note> God almightie appeared vnto me at Luze in the lande of Canaan and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me, in the which bliſſing was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined the promiſe of the hoped and performed ſauiour: and a litle before his laſt breath, he declareth his hope by theſe words: O Lord I haue waited for thy ſaluation:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 49.</note> and this was the comfort wherewith the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes comforted themſelues and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God: declaring it in ſuche ſorte as though the inſenſible creatures, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and the earth, the mountaines and the valleyes ſhould be refreſhed withall: ſuch was the prophecie of Eſaye.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 49.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce O heauens, and be ioyfull O earth, burſt forth into prayſe O mountaines, for God hath comforted his people, and will haue mercie on his afflicted. And by the prophet Zacharie thus ſaid the Lord: Reioyce with great ioy O daughter Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.</note> ſhoute for ioye O daughter Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, behold thy King commeth vnto thée, And by Micheas: And thou Bethléem in the land of Iuda art not the leaſt among the Princes of Iuda, for out of thée ſhall come the gouernour that ſhall féede my
<pb facs="tcp:8505:27"/>
people Iſraell: and to the comforte of the gentiles thus he ſaith, ſpeking as it were to his Chryſte: Beholde thou ſhalt call a nation that thou knoweſt not,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 55.</note> and a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that knewe not thée ſhall runne vnto thée, bicauſe of the Lord thy God, and the holy one of Iſraell: thus was Chryſte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a comforte for the hope of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to reſt vpon, and by him was their hope full with ioy: So did God loue them his choſen of Iſraell, that he hath ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gouernor that ſhould féede his people, he hath ſent them the good ſhepeherd that ſhould ſaue the loſt ſhepe. But this loue is ſuche that it reſteth not in the compaſſe of Ieruſalem, for S. Iohn ſaith, it is the loue wherewyth God loued the worlde. God hath ſent his ſonne and he hath ſent him, as well for the light and ioye of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, as for the glory of the Iewe: and we that knew not God may now know him: and nowe if fayth fayle not, it ſhall pleaſe God as well to be called the God of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande as the God of Iſraell: for he hath ſent the promiſed ſeede of Abraham, that ſhall bleſſe the one nation as well as the other, and he hath ſente his ſonne to
<pb facs="tcp:8505:27"/>
beſtowe his loue vpon all partes of the worlde, that in him all people ſhoulde be bleſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>The tenth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶What Chryste is, and in what ſtate he wrought the worke of our ſaluation.</head>
               <p>NOwe this hithervnto ſpoken, we haue béene thus farre in the fauor of God, and haue taſted howe gracious the Lorde is, that we know, euen for the loue he beareth vnto vs, he hath ſent vs a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer whiche ſhall be a reconciliation for vs, and ſhall quicken vs lying in the ſhadowe of death, that we might not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, but liue for euer: and who it is that he maketh our redéemer, as by the fleſhe the bleſſed ſéede of Abraham, a true man, and yet the onely begotten ſonne of God, him he hath not ſpared to make a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanger of ſaluation vnto the worlde, and this we knowe that God hath not giuen him to any other, rather than to vs, he is our Sauiour, if we be ſo happie as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, for we being graffed in Chriſte are members of that <hi>worlde</hi> which God ſo loueth: Nowe adding to this, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:8505:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by what meanes Chriſte wrought this reconciliation, how he hath through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye appeaſed the wrath of the father whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we ſee was ſo kindled againſt vs, and vnderſtanding what price he payde for our redemption, then ſhal the loue of God appeare vnto vs by a brighter light, &amp; as it were in a cléere ſunne ſhining. Oure Sauiour ſaythe, <hi>my father worketh and I worke,</hi> we haue ſéene the worke proper to the father, in that he hath ſent the ſonne, and thus farre forwarde we ſée our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in his worke, as that according to the determinate will of the father, he is come downe into the earthe, and hath debaſed himſelfe to the baſe eſtate of our frayle fleſh, ſo by this, the work of our regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in a goodly forwardneſſe, now doth Adam beginne to moue himſelfe, to waxe warme, and to reuiue with a newe ſpirit: here lyeth the Serpent a bléeding, but by this is not the victorie gotten. Let vs ſée then howe Chriſte quitteth himſelfe, and reuengeth our quarell. What force? what weapons doth he vſe? far other than man would imagine. He ouercommeth with kindneſſe: his armour is preaching,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:28"/>
paynes, pacience, ſhame, rebuke, reproch, harde handling, euill entreatie, tauntes in the teeth, and ſclaunderous reportes, ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſcourgings, falſe accuſations, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſte iudgement, and in the ende, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and bloudye death. This was the maruellous working of God, that oure Sauiour ſhoulde paſſe thoſe harde pykes to ſaue vs from the ſworde of the enimie. And beholde as ſoone as he entred into the world, he ſtraight gaue the onſet, he felte incontinently of our infirmities: for ſée the Lorde of Dauid, the King of Kings in his byrth howe ſimply he lyeth wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſwadling cloutes: Thus is it deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed in the Goſpell. A ſtable was his beſt houſe, and a cratche his Cradle,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 2.</note> for (ſaythe the Euangeliſt) there was no roume for him in the Inne: whoſe was the earth, and the ſtore thereof, at whoſe commaundemente were the heauens, there was no roume for him to reſte in. Well therefore might that complainte be made to the confuſion of vnkinde &amp; beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man. The Foxes haue holes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 8.</note> and the birdes of heauen haue neſts, but the ſonne of man howe is he intreated? he hath not
<pb facs="tcp:8505:29"/>
whereon to reſte his heade: Neither was he ſuffered to haue that litle roume wyth reſte, but he was faine to flée touch, and to auoyde from Bethléem into Egypt, as when Herode in his furie ſent forthe his ſlaughter men, and bloudie butchers, with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, that they ſhould ſlea all the male children that were in Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léem, and in all the coaſtes thereof, from two yeares old and vnder, ſeking thereby (as it was forewarned by the Angell) to murther the childe Ieſus, whom he heard ſhould be borne King of the Iewes. Such a welcome hadde our Sauiour into the world: and afterwarde in proceſſe of time being conuerſant in Hieruſalem, and the countrey about, with what trauell prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched he the kingdome of God? &amp; how few receiued that glad tydings? howe many a myracle did he? and what thanks had he? and how ſmall were the number of ſuche as beleeued, and woulde be content to be called the followers of Chryſte, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayning the name of a Chriſtian? Now when he was moſt buſy about the worke of our ſaluation, as when he was moſte occupied in feeding with the worde, and
<pb facs="tcp:8505:29"/>
conuerting by miracles, the reporte that many made of him, it was no better, but that his owne helde hym as a ſtraunger, ſome ſayde he was a ſinner,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 7.</note> ſome a ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the people, ſome a glutton and a drinker of wine, ſome a man ſtarke mad, yea, &amp; ſome gaue him this good word, that he wroughte by the power of Belzebub: Bitter wordes for the ſonne of God: yet this was his pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to beare. Of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſorte, ſome tooke him for Elias, ſome for Iohn Baptiſt, and ſome were ſo good as to call him a Prophete, but fewe were there found of faithfull Peters, that iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſo ryght of hym, as to ſay: Thou art the ſonne of the lyuing God. And wyth whome had our Sauioure his conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here on earthe? he was to be had in ſuche reputation, as of whome the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie father foreſpake by thys Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, euen hym that was bothe a king and a Prophete: I haue ſet my king vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sion myne holy mountayne:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note> and ſuche a one was he, as Dauid acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be hys Lorde and ſouereygne: The Lorde ſayde vnto my Lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.</note> ſitte thou at my right hand. &amp;c. It had bin ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:8505:30"/>
the parte of Princes to haue bin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in hys preſence, and the duetie of Kings to haue kept him company, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue attended on hym, as whoſe ſhooe latched they were not worthy to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſe: But true is the Prophet in his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> The Kings and Princes of the earth they aſſembled and bente themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte hym: there was no company nor comfort with them for the méeke King of Sion and the poore Prince of Ieruſalem. For we ſee howe Herode perſecuted and hunted him, as the Foxe the ſhéepe, from Bethléem to Egypt, from one place to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and it was treaſon to Ceſars per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to call Chriſt a King, he might not be taken for Ceſars friende that woulde ſpeake on Chriſtes parte to mainteyne hys kyngdome. But oure Sauiours kyngdome was not of thys worlde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no maruell though the kings of the earth were ſo cruelly ſet againſte hym: Our Sauioure was alſo the annointed of God, a Prince, and a princely Prieſt for euer, of whoſe body Melchiſedech was the ſhadowe, he was that Doctor admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and authoriſed to teache, with that
<pb facs="tcp:8505:30"/>
heauenly and thundering voyce of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>this is my beloued ſonne in vvhome I am vvell pleaſed, heare hym:</hi> it woulde haue beſemed therfore thoſe high prieſts, looked they neuer ſo high, that ruffling garde of Phariſies, thoſe greate Doctors the Scribes, to haue had their conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him, of whome they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their ſaluation: if they had harke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him then mighte they haue recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues wiſe, if they had followed that good ſhepehearde, then mighte they haue gloried truly, as otherwiſe they dyd vainely, that they had bene the leaders of the blinde. But Chriſt was not for their tooth, neyther any méete man for their company, he was a ſtone caſt aſide of thoſe builders, although hée approued hym ſelfe the chiefe corner ſtone: they could not reproue hym, yet they refuſed him: they myghte find no fault with hym, yet he could find no fauour with them, he put them many times to ſilence, and ſtopped their mouthes in reaſoning and argument, yet they ſpared no wordes in miſreporting him: he ſoughte all meanes to winne them, yet they diſdayned him
<pb facs="tcp:8505:31"/>
as one vnworthy to haue place amongſt them: for when that carnall ſpiritualitie, the high Prieſts and preſumptuous Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies ſawe that Chryſte and his doctrine began ſomewhat to be accepted of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they thinking that a derogation to their worſhips,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 7.</note> ſente out theyr officers to take Chriſte as he was teaching in the temple: but theſe officers although they came with full purpoſe to haue apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our ſauioure, yet ſo were they raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with hys heauenly preachings and wonderfull wordes flowing from hym ſo plentifully, that they had no power to doe their purpoſe, but retourned agayne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thys anſwere to their maiſters, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer man ſpake lyke thys man: but ſo was not the malice of thoſe hypocrites ſtayed, and with ſuche wordes they ſtormed and ſtamped againſt him continually, ſaying vnto thoſe their meſſangers: are ye alſo deceiued? dothe any of the Rulers, and of the Phariſies beleeue in him? but this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which knowe not the law are curſed: So did the Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deceiue them that they did ſtill ſpit their venome againſt that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted lambe that ſought their ſaluation:
<pb facs="tcp:8505:31"/>
they helde hym accurſſed that followed Chriſt: this ſuffered our Sauiour: the high Prieſts could not looke ſo low as to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine hym amongſt them: the Phariſies and Scribes in their owne conceit were to wiſe, to holy and to good, to take him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their company, it ſhoulde haue ſtayned their good name to be called Chriſtians, it was not for their worſhips to haue profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelues the diſciples of Chryſte: ſo was our Sauioure an abiecte, an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt, and made of no reputation, he was diſdained bothe of Prieſt and Prince, and this is maruellous in our eyes. But it was the good will of God, ſo to prouide for vs, that we ſhoulde not periſh: for Chriſte hereby hathe approued himſelfe the true annointed, the ſelfe Sauioure and very Meſſias, and Dauid alſo a true Prophet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.</note> ſaying: that the head ſtone of the corner ſhoulde be refuſed of the builders: they made no more of Chriſte than a ſtone to ſtumble and to ſpurne at: where then had our Sauioure his conuerſation? he betooke himſelfe (as he diſdained not the name of a phiſition comming to haue the ſicke) euen to be amongſt Publicanes and ſinners:
<pb facs="tcp:8505:32"/>
there was his company to viſite poore Publicanes, and to ſaue ſimple ſinners that was his comfort. This was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable tydings that he had to ſend Iohn Baptiſt into priſon, <hi>The blind ſee, the halt goe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>the leapers are cleanſed, the deafe heare, the dead riſe againe:</hi> This was his garde, he was ſtill buſie about theſe, the blinde, the Leaper, the lame, the deafe and the dead: in the meane ſpace where was the rich, the wiſe and the welthy? Nay they would not be taken for Chriſtes ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: but the poore (ſaythe he) receiue the glad tidings of the Goſpell: and happie it was that all fell not beſides, but that ther ſtoode ſome at receite to receiue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſéede ſowen by our Sauioure: thus we ſée a greate péece of the loue of God working in his ſonne our Sauioure: for what loue is this, that the ſonne of God ſhuld ſo humble himſelf to ſet vs in honor with his heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, but yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt péece of loue, and the chiefe token of gods mercy towards vs, is yet behind, and that which is vnſpoken is more than all that hertofore hath bin ſpoken: &amp; that doth S. Paule ſet forth after a moſt reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſort,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:32"/>
howbeit no man may vtter it with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy words: that place which I mean is in the ſeconde to the Philippians whome he exhorteth by the example of Chriſt to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and wherein for our purpoſe is to be ſéene the loue of God working in hys only begotten, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the vttermoſt point that may be imagined within al the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of loue, and in that he procéedeth by degrée, gathering vp in ſhorte ſumme all whiche is ſpoken in our former wordes concerning our Sauioure, that it myghte enter into vs with a déeper conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: this is his ſaying: <hi>let the ſame minde be in you that was euen in Chriſt Ieſus, who being in the forme of God, thought it no robberie to be equall with God, but he made hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of no reputation, and tooke vpon him the forme of a ſeruante, and was made like vnto men, and vvas founde in ſhape as a man:</hi> Here let vs ſtaye a while, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide Paules ſentence, kéeping backe that whiche followeth, vntill we haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what conſidered this parte of Gods loue, Chriſte the ſonne of God a verye God, a glorious God equal with the father, (and no wrong neyther) is come downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:33"/>
bright heauens to the bare earthe, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be made of mans mettall, taking on him very fleſhe, well pleaſed to be caſt in the mould and ſimple ſhape of man, no whit diſdaining the wombe of a woman, contente to be called the ſeede of Eue, and laying aſide his glory, and as it were hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his godhead, emptied himſelfe of all honoure, becomming of the ſonne of God the ſonne of man, like vnto man, a very man, a ſeruant of men, and what elſe but a ſlaue, to ſaue men: if there had here a ſtay bene made, yet might not the loue of God but ſéeme maruellous towardes man: But that which followeth in Saint Paule, that is muche more maruellous, that cannot but inflame the hearte of the Chriſtian with the loue of God, &amp; breake the ſtony ſtomack of the infidel. To what may I then compare thoſe wordes follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing? it is a thunderbolt that me thinkes ſhould ſound through the whole heauens, piercing the clouds and ſhaking the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the earthe, bringing with it a ſmoking fire, by the heate whereof the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mountaines melte lyke waxe, ioyned with a wind that hurleth downe the high
<pb facs="tcp:8505:33"/>
Ceders of Libanus: Harken then (O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) giue eare (O earth) ſée the loue of the almightie: he (ſaith the Apoſtle) euen that glorious God, beſide that he became man, in his manhoode he humbled himſelfe and became obedient: with what humilitie? howe farre was he obedient? euen to the death: what death? the death of the croſſe. Thys is that ſpeciall loue, <hi>God ſo loueth the world, that he hath giuen his ſonne</hi> to be a ſacrifice for our ſinnes, to be ſlayne that we might not periſhe, and to die that we might haue euerlaſting life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>The eleuenth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶A deſcription of the paſsion of Chriſte and the profite that commeth thereby.</head>
               <p>BVt yet that this loue mighte enter dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and take a more grounded roote in our hartes, let vs ſomewhat conſider the deathe of the Lorde, let vs ſée what a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiue he had to his cup, let vs marke the maner of his deathe, and let vs behold him with our inward eyes in hys pangs as hee hangeth on the croſſe: thys there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did our Sauioure forewarne his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb facs="tcp:8505:34"/>
what ſhould become of him, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we haue alſo a warning to conſider the loue of God:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 20.</note> Beholde (ſaith he) we goe vp to Ieruſalem, and the ſonne of man ſhall be deliuered into the handes of ſinners, vnto the chiefe Prieſtes &amp; vnto the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, &amp; they ſhall condemne him to deathe, and ſhall deliuer him to the Gentiles to mock, and to ſcourge, and to crucifie him. This did our Sauioure foreſee as a God, and fulfill as a man ſent to redeeme men: firſte when the tyme of hys temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on drewe neare, hys ſchollers began to ſcatter and fléete from hym vntill they lefte hym cleane withoute company and comfort. For ſome faynting by default of faith he draue away with a word,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he gaue them that leſſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eating of the fleſh and drinking of the bloude of the ſonne of man: thys is a harde ſaying (ſaye they) who can away with thys? ſo they gaue ouer ſchoole and followed their maiſter no further. Then thoughte our Sauior good to make much of his twelue, and therefore to holde in them, that they ſhoulde not ſtart lykewiſe, he turned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them as it were grating kindneſſe on
<pb facs="tcp:8505:34"/>
them with thys pitifull queſtion: and wyll you alſo goe from me? Peters ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke was yet ſomewhat ſtout, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he anſwered the queſtion with thys other: Maſter to whome ſhall we goe? thou haſt the words of eternall life. That was Chriſtes chiefe captaine: it was to be thought he would haue a bidden the brunt, but of hym it ſhall be ſayde after. Nowe by thys time Chriſt had but his choſen twelue with him, and yet one of them was but a traytor, yea a diuell. For in that heauy feaſt and laſt ſupper, whereat he tooke hys leaue as it were of his diſciples: then began Satan to ſtirre himſelfe, to aſſaulte and ſift the ſimple ſouldiers of Chriſte, and tooke full poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Iudas to worke by hym that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible treaſon againſte our poore Prince, which ſought by kyndneſſe to ouercome his enimies: for he as ſoone as he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that choaking morſell the ſoure ſop, he got him out about the Deuils bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, ſéeking our ſauiours death and his own deſtruction. And for his farewel, ſaith Chriſte, that thou doeſt, doe quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, for belyke he felte panges of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb facs="tcp:8505:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8505:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8505:36"/>
alreadie vppon him, wherefore vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this his departure, hée comforted himſelfe and the reſt of his diſciples with thoſe and the lyke ſayings as did declare the prouidence of God the Father in thys behalfe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.</note> verily (ſayeth hée) it goeth wyth the ſonne of man as it is written of hym: it was wrytten, hée that eateth breade with mée,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.</note> lifteth vp his heele agaynſte me. Whyles that Iudas and theſe blouddie merchantes were buſie aboute theyr bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, valuyng that innocent and ſauing ſoule at .xxx. ſiluerlings, Chriſt wyth part of his Diſciples went vp into the Mounte Oliuet to make his prayer: where howe bitter were his temptations? In what an agonie was hée?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.</note> when thoſe bloudye droppes of ſweate trickled downe along that ſwéete glorious face? what deepe ſighes did hée fetche? out of howe heauie an heart did theſe ſayings procéede: firſt to his Diſciples, ſaying, my ſoule is verie heauie vnto death: then in his lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayer: O my father, if it bée poſſible, let this cuppe paſſe from mée? and yet in this diſtreſſe hée humbled him ſelfe, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting his will to the will of his father.
<pb facs="tcp:8505:36"/>
Nowe after this fitte was paſte, and hée had ouercommed that temptation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde thoſe Wolues, that bloudie band ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by the high Prieſtes and Phary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies commeth oute with theyr Lanternes and lightes, as to make ſearch for a théefe, with ſtaues and ſwordes, as agaynſt a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious traytour, laying handes on hym as on a miſchieuous murtherer. And who was theyr Capitayne? euen that loſt childe Iudas, he became theyr guyde:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2</note> hée tracked oure Sauiour in hys waye, hée led thoſe murtherers ouer the brooke Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, he brought them into the Garden,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18.</note> where they founde that ſillie ſhéepehearde with his ſmall flocke, that méeke henne hauing no where to hide his heade, with his little broode of Chickens tremblyng and ſhaking about him for feare, loking for ſuccour vnder the ſhadowe of his wings, who himſelfe was nowe deſtitute of all earthly ayde: this alſo might not but aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his ſorowes, that in the ſame place in that garden, where they had ſo often gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red togyther to theyr comfort, and where Iudas himſelfe had bene diuerſe tymes fed at our Sauiors hand with the ſwéet bread
<pb facs="tcp:8505:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of life, there he ſhould be gyuen vp to the hands of ſinners: &amp; how was he betraied? Euen as that lamentable queſtion impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudas betrayeſt thou the ſonne of man vvith a kiſſe?</hi> Whiche was to ſaye, thou whom I haue choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many a thouſand, one of my twelue familiaes, thou vppon whome I haue beſtowed ſo many good turnes, to whome I haue gyuen fréely ſo many good leſſons, vppon whome I haue waſted ſo many wordes, thou that eateſt bread with me, thou that dippedſt in one diſh with me, doſt thou lift vp thy héele a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and tread me vnder thy foote? thou that prouidedſt for the ſuſtenance of my body, art thou become the betrayer of my ſoule? whoſe ſaluation I haue ſought by ſo many meanes, doeſt thou thirſt my bloud? for whome I am contente to laye downe my life, art thou become my hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? Commeſt thou vnto me with the face of a friend, and giueſt me vp to mine enimies? Calleſt thou me maiſter, and wiſheſt me the curſe of the croſſe? Gyueſt thou me a kiſſe, and woundeſt my harte? Theſe ſighes no doubte came vp with that queſtion. Nowe by this time had
<pb facs="tcp:8505:37"/>
Iudas done hys parte, he myght go hang hymſelfe: In thys caſe then we ſée our Sauioure, howe he ſtandeth as a poore priſoner deliuered into the hands of hys mortall enimies, being hymſelfe an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall God. He that might haue had at hys call a legion of Aungels to deliuer him, is yet contented to become a priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, a captiue and as a caytiue, rather than he woulde breake off thys worke of our redemption whiche he had brought ſo neare to perfection. What then follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed? the ſhepeherde was ſtricken, and the ſheepe were ſcattered: and alas poore Peter what reſiſtance maiſt thou make? Put vp thy ſword, and harken what thy Sauiour ſaithe: yea let vs all harken to that voice of humilitie: ſhall I not drink of the cup whiche my father hath gyuen me?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18.</note> So Chriſt ſtill fighteth with pacience euen till he maketh his enimies his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole: for beholde he is bounde wyth paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by the hande, the captaine and the officers of the Iewes: ſo as it was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of hym, he was led as a ſhéepe brought before the ſheerer, to Annas that ſharpe ſhéerer: then was he turned and toſſed
<pb facs="tcp:8505:38"/>
from one to another, from poſt to piller, from the Foxe to the Wolfe, from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas to Cayphas, from Cayphas to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas againe, and ſtill faſt bound for feare of ſcaping. O what an heauie ſighte, what a payne was that for Peter, when he ſawe his Maſter ſtanding lyke a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken ſoule, and a pitifull priſoner in the hall of the high Prieſt? Now where was that ſtout, courage when he ſaide, though all men bée offended for thee,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 26.</note> yet I wyll not? He followed hys maiſter indeede: but a farre off for feare. And when hée came to the dore of the high Prieſte, in what a traunce, in what a terroure was he? where was his ſword? now wher was his heart, when the maid moued him this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: art not thou one of this mans diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples? what had he then to anſwer? he made then a flat deniall of hys maiſter, he was none of his diſciples, he knewe no ſuche man as Chriſte was: and nowe was it tyme for the cocke to crowe, for Peter to fall a weeping and a howling: there was Chriſte left alone and giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer on euery ſide, for the ſhéepe they were all diſperſed. Now that guiltleſſe Lambe
<pb facs="tcp:8505:38"/>
with what a ſorte of wicked wolues was he beſet? There was Annas the fyrſte, Caiphas the high Prieſte, Pilate the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, there was the aſſembly of Scribes, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocke of Phariſies: but thankes be to God the heauenly father, his Chriſte had pacience ynough for them all. There was in that Lambe bloude ynough for thoſe greedy wolues the rulers and gouernors, there were bones ynough for thoſe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie dogges the Scribes, and fleſhe to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie that ſwarme of adders the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: for all thoſe there was pacience y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough with our ſuffring ſauiour, being ready to beare what ſoeuer burthen they might deuiſe to oppreſſe him wythall: for they bounde him, they made a ſcorne and a mock of him, turning him into a ſtrange diſguiſed apparell, platting a crowne of thornes vpon his heade, adding thereto thorny and gauling wordes, beyng haled and toſſed to and fro betwixt Pilate, the Prieſtes and the people:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.</note> one crying on this ſide, beholde the man, in diſpite of his omnipotent godheade: on the other ſyde another company crying, hayle Kyng of the Iewes, in contempt of this eternall
<pb facs="tcp:8505:39"/>
kingdome: and yet for further tryall of his pacience ſome blindfelded hym, ſome buffetted him, ſome moſte ſhamefullye ſpued theyr ſpettle on his face: then was hée tormented alſo wyth Pylates bitter ſcourge, &amp; yet no reſiſtance made Chriſt: remedie was pacience: but that was not thought ynoughe, neyther ſcourging woulde not ſerue: therefore he muſte bée committed againe to the handes of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, hée muſte be examined, witneſſe is ſought, and falſe witneſſe is brought in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the truth it ſelfe, yea although Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late himſelfe, coulde not but thus depoſe for his innocencie, ſaying and repeating it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>I finde no fault in hym:</hi> wherefore yet thys friendſhip was ſhewed of Pylate, that the people contented, he ſhoulde bée let looſe according to the cuſtome of the Iewes: This was the greateſt curteſie that Chriſte founde: he was ſet agaynſte Barrabas: an holy God compared wyth a wicked murtherer: for ſo did Pylate put it to the peoples choyſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 27.</note> ſaying: Wil ye that I let looſe vnto you Barrabas, or Ieſus whiche is called Chriſt? naye, if Chriſt ſhould haue nowe bene let at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:39"/>
then had the Prieſtes his enimies fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning loſt al their labor: wherfore Mathewe reporteth that they counſelled the people to quite Barrabas, and to aſke Chriſt to be crucified, wherefore the ſauing and condemnation being referred vnto them, when they cried for Barrabas that he might be ſaued, then Pylate ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſomwhat fauourably as he durſt, on Chriſtes part, ſayd: what ſhall I do then with Ieſus? the anſwere was: let him be crucified. And Pylate demaunding again, what euill hath he done? That queſtion might not be heard, bycauſe it coulde not be aunſwered, but the more they cryed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with him, crucifie him. This was that rufull crie that Chriſte was content to heare, for all the loue of God that was and ſhoulde be declared by him towardes the worlde, he had this rewarde, crucifie him &amp; nothing but crucifie him. After this hard ſentence, as a lamb to the ſlaughter, ſo was our Sauioure led out of the Citie to the place of his executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.</note> hauing the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of his Croſſe, and bearing it part of the way himſelfe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 21.</note> Now muſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our be ſerued as the Serpent in the wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:40"/>
he muſt be lifte vp to the croſſe: beholde he drinketh the cup of that curſe: (Curſed is he that hangeth on the trée:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. <hi>Gene.</hi> 22.</note>) This is the true repreſented Iſaacke, that humbleth himſelfe to the aultar a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſinne, and the Lorde ſuffereth that bloudy knife withdrawn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iſaack, to fall vpon his onely begotten ſonne and to pierce his precious bowelles that the water mought runne out whiche ſhoulde waſhe away the ſinnes of his people. O Chriſtians, O men and brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this was ours by right, but Chriſte is contented to beare our burthen, he is contented to dye, to dye the death, the ſhamefull deathe, the curſed death of the bitter croſſe. Nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the Lamb of God, that taketh away the ſinnes of the worlde: O thou ſonne of man ſée what the ſonne of God ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for thy ſake, ſée how he is tormented. let his panges enter a little into thy hart, that thou mayſte conſider the loue of God towardes thee, lette that pitifull ſcricke of our Sauiour alwayes ring in thyne eare, as when he cryed, my God my God why haſt thou forſaken me: for ſo did the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of death gripe him as thoughe he
<pb facs="tcp:8505:40"/>
had indéede bene forſaken of his father: wherefore he ſuffered him to be layde in the graue alſo, that he might taſt of al our infirmities as well vnder the earth as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue: howbeit nowe was it time for the Lord God to gloryfie his ſonne in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, which had glorified him on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.</note> wherefore he might not leaue the ſoule of his dearely beloued in the graue, nor ſuffer his holye one to ſée corruption: but hath rayſed him vp to his ryght hande, there to reigne with glorie vntil he make his enimies and our enimies, (if we be true Chriſtians) his footeſtoole: and thus with the glorie of Chriſte doth the loue of God fully appeare, towardes vs: for in all this hath God and his Chryſte ſought our ſaluation:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> for the ſonne of man came for no other purpoſe, but to ſaue that which was loſte, and by theſe meanes in ſumme hathe he atchieued the ende of his meſſage:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> he was deliuered to deathe for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:41"/>
               <head>The tvvelfth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶How only faith wrought in vs by the ſpirit of God, and grounded vpon the word of God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs partakers of the fruit of Chriſtes death.</head>
               <p>THus is that worthy worke finiſhed. Nowe may Abraham reioyce with ful ioy, for his promiſed ſéede is performed, and he hath poured out his bleſſing moſte plentifully vpon his faithfull children: now is Adam truly made vp a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; thus far is he in the fauor of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath ſent his only begotten ſon to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe him his pardon: God ſaid in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation: <hi>thou ſhalt die the death:</hi> (but ſo hath the ſonne pleaſed him, that he nowe cryeth:) <hi>thou ſhalt not periſhe, but haue life euerlaſting:</hi> Nowe ſhalte thou liue, for ſo God loueth thée that Chriſt hath dyed in thy ſtead: now mayſt thou ſtand vpright, for ſo God loueth thée, that his Chryſte hath falne for thee: Chryſte is ryſen and beholde he ſo loueth thée, that he offereth his gentle hande to rayſe thée togyther with himſelfe: he hath deceyued the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that deceyued thee: he ſhall make his enimies his footeſtoole, and he hathe
<pb facs="tcp:8505:41"/>
troden thy enimies vnder his féete, for this is thy ſéede that hathe cruſhed his heade: he hath obtayned a crowne of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and he maketh thée alſo a glorious conquerour: Al this no doubt did S. Iohn conſider in the loue of God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wrote this worthy ſaying of our Sauiour, <hi>God ſo loueth the world, that he hath giuen his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten ſonne,</hi> that he ſhoulde liue with vs, bycauſe we were deade to him, that he ſhoulde dye for vs, to the ende we myghte liue with him, that he ſhoulde enter into the earth, to make vs an entry into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens. We haue by this ſéene ſome ſhadow of the maruellous worke of God concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning oure redemption: we ſée the louing worke of God the father, whoſe proper praiſe it is, that he hath ſent his ſonne: we haue ſeene alſo the painfull worke of God the ſonne who hath ſuffered as we ſée: nowe haue we to conſider the worke of the holy ſpirite likewiſe, whoſe worke it is that we enioye thoſe benefites ſente vs by the father, &amp; brought by the Sonne: for in whoſe hart that ſpirit worketh not, to him is the Croſſe of Chryſte altogy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruitleſſe, to him is Ieſus no Ieſus,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:42"/>
that is, no Sauioure, and he may inioy no part of that loue of God whiche bringeth life with it: for what? now God hath ſent his ſonne, is that ſufficiente for vs? haue we withoute any further adoe taken poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of heauen? are we ſtreight by thys in the boſome of Abraham? ſhall we now take no further care? is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Croſſe of Chriſt accepted an excuſe, indifferently for all? ſhall euery ſoule be ſaued? Nay let no man deceiue hymſelfe: Chriſte indeede hathe made an entry into Heauen, he hath ſet open a gate vnto vs: but yet a ſtrayght gate where fewe ſhall enter: neyther yet is the gate of Hell cleane ſhut vp: no it ſtandeth wide ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a gaping mouth, and many ſhall go that way. In the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall flocke, Chriſte hathe his ſheepe, and they are the fewer: he hath alſo his gotes, and they are the greater part? There is in Gods field good corne, but that is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growen with euill chaffe: there be ſome likewiſe that ſhall be receiued with the right hand: O happie are they, for Chriſte is theirs altogyther: there are alſo whoſe place is prouided on the left hande: O vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie are they, for they haue no parte in
<pb facs="tcp:8505:42"/>
Chriſt: let vs therefore looke vnto our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation whiles yet the light ſhineth, for as much as there is a little flocke which that good ſheephearde hath choſen to himſelfe, let vs get into the folde with them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 13.</note> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his councell, let vs ſtriue to enter in at the ſtrayt gate, and that in tyme, leaſt the dore be ſhutte againſt vs, when it ſhall be to late to knocke: Chriſt is ſent vnto vs, let vs beware that we receyue him: Chriſt hath brought this rewarde with him, to as many of vs as do receyue him: <hi>(that we ſhoulde not periſhe, but liue for euer.)</hi> Let vs therefore prouide that we léeſe not oure part in that precious pearle: what then is there nowe to be done? Verily nowe we haue ſéene the loue of God declared by Chriſt, there is but one ſteppe betwixt vs and home, but one worde betwixt vs and lyfe euerlaſting: neyther hathe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Euangeliſt left that out of his place: for thoſe are the footeſteppes he poynteth out vnto vs, the loue of God the father, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and croſſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galath.</hi> 6</note> finally faith the good gift of the holy Ghoſt: for this is the condition: <hi>who ſo beleeueth in Chriſt ſent from God,</hi> he ſhould be ſure not to periſhe,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:43"/>
but to haue life euerlaſting. Nowe then muſt we make prouiſion for beléefe, that fayth faile not, this muſt be all our care: for what ſhall it profit vs though Chriſt come into the worlde, and come againe, if he bée not receyued of vs. By fayth he muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, or elſe he muſt be refuſed: his owne receyued him not ſayth S. Iohn:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.</note> and why, but for lacke of faith? for to as many as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued him, to them he gaue power to bée the ſonnes of God: and what were they? euen to them ſayth he, that beleeue in hys name: accordingly as S. Paule ſaith to the Galathians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.</note> by fayth are ye the ſonnes of God: the beleeuers then they are the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonnes of God, they are the right recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Chriſt: when that Chriſt the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, firſt appeared amongſt vs, then did the Angelles proclayme peace betwixt heauen and earth, and from God good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will towardes men: for Chriſt indeede is the true Melchiſedech, that is, the King that brought peace wyth hym into the worlde. But what ſhall all this auayle vs, if we beléeue not?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> for ſo ſayth our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelfe, he that beléeueth in the ſonne hath euerlaſting life, and he that obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:8505:43"/>
not the ſonne, ſhall not ſée lyfe, but the wrath of God abydeth vpon him: ſo wrath remayneth for the infidell, what then for the faythfull? there is peace kept in ſtore for him as for a faythfull ſubiect to the king of peace: for we béeing iuſtified by fayth, haue peace with God through our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>Luke.</hi> 2.</note> that is the ſaying of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. Chriſt is appoynted for the fall of many: who are they but the faythleſſe? he is ordeyned alſo to bée the ryſing of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and who are they but the faythfull? for ſo ſayth oure Sauiour likewiſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> (who can not belie himſelfe,) hée that beléeueth in him, he ſhall not bee condemned: hée that beléeueth not is alreadye condemned, bycauſe hée beléeueth not in the name of the onely begotten Sonne of GOD. Chriſt is alſo a ſtone of diuerſe operations:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> hee is a precious ſtone, and hée is lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe a ſtumbling ſtone. To whome then is it precious but to ſuche, as by ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the iewell of fayth therevnto, haue the right vſe thereof. So ſayeth the Scripture.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28.</note> Beholde I put in Sion a chiefe corner ſtone electe and precious, and hée that beléeueth therein ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:8505:44"/>
be aſhamed: and here Saint Peter maketh this concluſion, ſaying: to you therefore which beléeue it is precious, this part is for the beléeuer, nowe muſt the infidell take that which is left: they haulting for want of the ſteadie foote of fayth, make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of Chriſt a ſtone to ſtumble at, and a rocke of offence: although Chriſt be ſet vp vnto them a ſigne of ſaluation, yet they like the Cocke on the dunghill, do ſpurne him aſide, not knowing what vertue there is layde vp in that precious ſtone, for ſuch as by fayth doe finde him: wherefore that Prophecie is their portion:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 8. <hi>Math.</hi> 21.</note> whoſoeuer ſhall fall on this ſtone, he ſhall be broken: and on whome ſoeuer it falleth, it ſhall grinde him to powder: the miſbeléeuers they ſtumble and lie vnder the ſtone, they fall and are fallen on, therefore muſt they be broken, and that grinding ſtone ſhall grinde them to powder. O the rocke of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie that maketh Chriſt the rocke of offence, that rocke it is that ſhattereth our ſhippes, that ſhooteth vs on the ſandes, but the anchor of fayth faſt fixed on the ſure ground Chriſt, hauing holde by his worde, that neuer deceyueth him that hopeth for
<pb facs="tcp:8505:44"/>
helpe, that ſaueth vs ſounde from ſtorme and tempeſt, from all winde and weather, he maketh ſure worke that worketh by the worthie and ſure inſtrument of fayth, and he buildeth once for all that hath Chriſt laid for his foundation, directing himſelfe alway by the right rule of his worde: for they that come to that liuely ſtone, they are a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall houſe as Saint Peter ſayth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.</note> yea they are the ſure grounded and glorious temple of the liuing God: thus then we being buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp by faith, &amp; caſting anchor on Chriſt, nowe let the floudes aryſe, let the windes blowe, yet ſtande we ſure, for we beléeue in him that will ſée we do not periſhe, thoſe that are in that raging ſea of the wilde wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked worlde, they ſéeme to ſtande in great daunger of ſhipwracke, but if we enter the Arke by fayth with Noe, (for S. Paule at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributeth his fauour vnto fayth) then let the Pyrates come, let Satan aſſaulte vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> yet are we harmeleſſe, Chriſt is on oure ſyde, what maye preuaile againſt vs? not ſands, not Rockes, not ſtormes nor tempeſtes, no windes ne floudes, nor fire nor water, no not all the power of Satan, not the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping gates of hell ſhall moue vs a whitte.
<pb facs="tcp:8505:45"/>
Such commoditie doe thoſe finde that be ſo happie as to enioy the ineſtimable iewell of faith: but thoſe that haue no experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and féele not the force of faith, they make light of the matter, not ſéeking Chriſt by faith, nor faith by his word, and therfore no marueyl though they be ſtil ouerſhadowed with death, &amp; being in darkneſſe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended not the light: howe ſhould they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue except they heare?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> fayth commeth by hearing, hearing of the word of God. They then that haue loſt their hearing, howe ſhoulde they finde fayth? where the ſéede of the worde is not ſowne, how ſhoulde the fruite of fayth ſpring? howe may they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy Chriſt or any part of his loue that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue not his witneſſes?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> The Scriptures (ſayth Chriſt) they beare witneſſe of mée. Theſe things ſayth S. Iohn,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 20.</note> meaning the contents of the Goſpell, are written, that ye might beléeue that Ieſus is Chriſt the ſon of God, and that in beléeuing ye myght haue lyfe through his name. Wherefore vnderſtande ye that vpon this double point ſtandeth the whole courſe of oure ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: art thou in the right waye? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then it is, bicauſe thou haſt followed
<pb facs="tcp:8505:45"/>
the counſell of our ſauiour, ſaying:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſearche the ſcriptures.</hi> Art thou out of the way? The cauſe learne of Chriſt: <hi>ye are deceyued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>not knowing the Scriptures.</hi> This is the marke wherewith Chriſt marketh his ſhéepe, by the voyce we know our ſhepeheard, and by hearing we are knowne of him:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.</note> my ſhéepe heare my voyce (ſayth that good ſhepeherd) and I knowe them and they followe mée: Thus knowe where we haue to fetche fayth, that wée bée not to ſéeke on this ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, where we finde alſo howe God loueth the worlde, in prouiding ſo mercifullye the lyuely foode of his worde, that our ſoules faint not in fayth: but let vs treade a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle deeper in thys matter, and that wée maye value faythe ſomewhat neere the worthie pryce it ſhoulde beare with vs, let vs conſider howe the market goeth with vs, let vs conſider in what caſe wée ſtand: then ſhall we ſee what ſeruice faith will doe vs: firſt this we knowe, that we haue but borrowed breath and that lying in our noſtrelles, as the ſcripture ſpeaketh: our life what is it but a plaine warfare? wherein we haue either to yéeld or to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come? we vnderſtande with what enimies
<pb facs="tcp:8505:46"/>
we are beſet, as that wily witch the world, the prowde ſwelling fleſhe euer rebelling agaynſt the ſpirit: the ſerpent and his ſeede dayly ſpetting out his fierie flames and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous poyſon vpon vs, Satan I meane that ramping roring Lion continually ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſearching how to deuour vs. Now he that muſt abide the brunt of ſuch a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, and hath to encounter with ſo fierce and cruell aduerſaries, as whome we ſée dayly murthering many a ſoule, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie that ſuch a ſouldiour ſhoulde go well appoynted to the fielde. Wherefore in this behalfe it ſhall be good we follow the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Saint Paule,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.</note> who ſpeaketh not without booke, but of experience (for hée fought a good fight) his councell is, that we put on the armour of God, and this is the furniture that he appointeth for to arme ſuche a Souldiour as we ſeeke. He wiſheth our loynes to be gyrded with veritie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing on the breaſtplate of righteouſneſſe, oure féete being ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace: But aboue all (ſayeth he) take vnto you the ſhield of faith wherewith ye may quenche all the fierie dartes of the wicked: and Saint Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:8505:46"/>
likewiſe ſtrong in the ſpirite, he giueth vs good inſtruction, and warneth vs whiche waye we may winne the fielde. All that is borne of God (ſayth he) ouercommeth the worlde,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5.</note> and this is the victorie that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the worlde, euen our fayth: then he addeth this queſtion with his anſwere: who is it that ouercommeth the worlde,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5.</note> but he whiche beleeueth that Ieſus is the ſonne of God? And S. Peter alſo when he had declared what an aduerſarie we haue of the deuill, as that lyke a roaring Lyon he ſéeketh to deuour vs, then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth he this exhortation ſhewing howe we may ſtande agaynſt the aſſaultes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan: reſiſt him (ſayth he) ſtedfaſt in the fayth. Thus is fayth commended vnto vs of all hands, as a ſhielde to defende vs in all aſſaultes, and as a ſure tryed weapon to conquere and beate downe to the duſt, the diuell, the worlde, and all that ſtande agaynſt vs, it is Chriſt in déede that hath gotten the victorie, but ſuche is his loue, he dothe not enioy it alone, but he giueth vs part alſo. Thus he comforteth vs lyke a captayne of courage: be of good chéere,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16.</note> for I haue ouercommed the worlde. He
<pb facs="tcp:8505:47"/>
fought the fight indéede, he hath taken the fort, but he giueth vs the ſpoyle, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that his victorie be accounted our victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſo ſpeaketh Saint Paule, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the loue of God therein:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> Thankes be to God (ſayth he) which hath giuen vs victorie through our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt: and howe hath Chriſt giuen vs the victory, but as he ſayeth, fayth quencheth the fierie dartes of the wicked, and as Saint Iohn ſayth, our faith in Chriſt ouercommeth the worlde, and as Saint Peter exhorteth, by ſtedfaſtneſſe of fayth to reſiſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill? Suche is the marueylous vertue of true beliefe, that by it we enioye all the fruites whiche ſpring ſo plenteouſly oute of that flouriſhing roote of Iſhai: for Chriſt had ſubdued ſinne:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 11.</note> ſo haue wée by fayth in Chriſte: Chriſte by death hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commed death: ſo haue we by faith: Chriſt is proued by ſuffering a Sauiour, and wée by fayth are ſaued: Chriſt by his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath purchaſed to himſelfe an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting kingdome: and wée ryſing in hym by faith are ioyned in that purchaſe. Chriſt by nature is the ſonne of God, ſo are wée of his grace by fayth: finally Chriſt is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither
<pb facs="tcp:8505:47"/>
ours by fayth, which doth incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate all Chriſtians into his miſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: Chriſt (as Saint Paule ſayth) is our peace: howe but by fayth? as he ſayth,<note place="margin">Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> we beeing iuſtified by fayth haue peace wyth God: and the Apoſtle ſayeth that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Chriſt is our righteouſneſſe, and howe is that but by fayth? Chryſtes holyneſſe is our ſanctification, his iuſtice is our iuſtification: all this commeth by none other meanes: than as Saint Paule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth when Chriſte dwelleth in oure heartes by fayth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.</note> we are filled wyth all fulneſſe of God: ſuche then is the force of fayth, that wyth this one counter we may ſhortly caſt the whole ſumme of oure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. For art thou not deade to God, but lyueſt vprightly before him in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Abacuc.</hi> 2.</note> then haſte thou fayth, for the iuſt lyueth by fayth. Art thou wicked and ſinfull: no marueyle if thou haſt not fayth, for whatſoeuer is not of fayth is ſinne? thys is the roote,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> we are the trées, the reſt as oure good workes they are but flowers and fruites. Nowe ſuche as the roote is, ſuche is the trée, and ſuch as the trée is, ſuche is the fruite: for
<pb facs="tcp:8505:48"/>
Chriſt maketh no more differences of trées and fruites, but as in the Goſpell. Either make the trée good and his fruit good, or elſe make the trée euill and his frute euill: and what is that that maketh this difference but fayth the roote of all righteouſneſſe? for vnleſſe by this meanes we be truly graffed in Chriſt the true vine, all that we doe, it were as good vndone, as good neuer a whit as neuer the better, we make but wood for the fire,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15.</note> it is in effect nothing, but as hée ſayth, without me ye can do nothing: and our workes whatſoeuer ſhew they haue, if they be not rooted in Chriſt by fayth, they are neither figges nor grapes, but verie thornes and thiſtles, well may they grow for a while, but they may not flouriſh long: euen as herbes that growe in the ſhadowe, neuer well weathered with the warme ſunne: or rather as the graſſe on the houſe top which lacketh his roote, and therefore although it ſpringeth in the Sommer ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet it ſoone withereth in the Winter, and the mower neuer filleth his hand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. Let thoſe then that ſéeme fruitful in good workes, conſider of what roote that ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: for the beleeuer worketh well moued
<pb facs="tcp:8505:48"/>
by fayth, and his fruite is life euerlaſting: but the miſbeléeuing hypocrite he worketh of glory, and he hath his rewarde, miſſing farre of the right marke of righteouſneſſe: all that he maketh is marred for lacke of beléefe, his works are naught but bare lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of the fruitleſſe figge trée, they are but paintings and ſhadowes, mockings and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh toies in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of that iuſtice of the iuſt liuing by faith: for what is he that flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth neuer ſo much in his painted grapes and wel coloured fruites, which is able to pleaſe God vnleſſe he be a true trée, planted of the heauenly father, in the faith of chriſt? what fruit is it that God will allowe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be fet by fayth of the true vine? doeſt thou faſt? well done if it be done in fayth: doeſt thou giue almes to the poore? doeſt thou breake thy bread to the néedie? doeſt thou cloth the naked, and ſuccour the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourleſſe? Good fruites verily, therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like they come of a good trée, whoſe roote is fayth, watered with the precious bloud of our Sauiour. Doeſt thou withdrawe thy handes from iniurie? then doeſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue of likelihood: doeſt thou ſuffer wrong with pacience? a good ſigne it is that thou
<pb facs="tcp:8505:49"/>
art alreadie iuſtified by fayth: and all thoſe with ſuch like good works of men, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they are not meritorious, but with fayth they are acceptable: for ſo general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaketh the Apoſtle: without fayth it is vnpoſſible to pleaſe God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b.</hi> 12.</note> Marke, this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie hath with it an impoſſibilitie: but contrariwiſe if thou haue fayth, feare not, for that bringeth a poſſibilitie: ſo large is the promiſe of Chriſt ſpeaking to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuers: Nothing ſhall bée vnpoſſible vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> O great is the force of fayth, as the whiche to withſtande it is impoſſible: a little fayth is muche worth, and will go farre, yea, although it be but as much as a grayne of Muſtarde ſéede, it ſhall plucke vp the rootes of ſinne, yea let the diuell caſt vp Mountaynes agaynſt vs, yet will it haue his frée courſe, and may not be ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from Chriſt, whatſoeuer ſtandeth in the way: it is whole in ſickneſſe, frée in bandes, ſtrong in torments, it ſhyneth in darkeneſſe, it dyeth not with death, it is caſt into the waters, and periſheth not, it is tried in the fiery fornace and yet waſteth not: it is troden downe, but it ryſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:49"/>
it is aſſaulted, but neuer yéeldeth: it is wounded, but yet getteth the victory. Such as Chryſt is, ſuch is the fayth of the Chriſtian: Chriſt is the body, fayth is the ſhadow: where ſo Chriſt goeth, there faith fayleth not to followe. It is no earthly thing, but as Chryſt came from the hyghe heauens, ſo is that the heauenly gift of the holy Ghoſt. Where Chriſte is occupied, fayth is not ydle, when Chryſte worketh myracles in the body, fayth worketh ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in the ſoule, when Chriſte vttered the worde, fayth printed in the heart, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he fed the body with bread, he fed the ſoule with faith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpittle was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane to heale the eye, but faith the inſtrument to ſaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, fayth hath his courſe with Chriſt in al places to al purpoſes, it folowed Chriſt to the temple, to the mountaine, it was with him in the fielde, in the houſe, on the Sea, on the lande, it abydeth with him in temptations, in torments, it ſuffreth the ſcourge with him, it hangeth on him on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, it goth into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue with him, it ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with him, it foloweth him through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clouds, as it were with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wings of an Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, entring the heauens after him &amp; there
<pb facs="tcp:8505:50"/>
findeth foode to féede on, where Chriſte ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth hir to hang on his breſt, and to ſucke of his precious bloud vntill ſhe be ſatiſfied. Thus is faith exalted, that it taketh vp hir place in the high heauens, and is ſtill ſo far in fauour with God, that it can no rather call, but it is heard, no rather aſke, but it obtaineth, no ſoner ſeeke but it findeth, no rather knock, but it is opened vnto hir. So doth fayth worke for the beleeuer: for he is the beloued of god, to him is the ſonne ſent, he receiueth the ſonne: Chriſte is his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, the death of Chriſt is his life, Chriſt taketh him vp with him in his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Chriſt is altogither his, and who maye reſiſte him? <hi>for God ſo loueth him that by Chriſt he ſhall not periſhe but haue life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>The thirtenth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶That true faith requireth an earnest conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mans estate, and the loue of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him, appearing in the death of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>THus haue we waded in the bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſea of Gods loue &amp; infinite mercy, wherewith he loueth and embraceth the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:50"/>
worlde, not minding to finde any ende, or to ſearch the grounde thereof (for we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with the Prophete.) Thy mercy O Lord reacheth vnto the heauens,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.</note> and thy faythfulneſſe vnto the cloudes, thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is like the mightie mountaines, and thy iudgementes are like a greate deepe: but by this which is ſayde we haue aſſaid ſomewhat to taſt of the goodneſſe of God, following herein the prouocation of the Prophete, whiche calleth men to the conſideration of Gods mercy by this call: O taſt and ſée (ſaith he) how gracious the Lorde is: Bleſſed is the man that putteth his truſt in his mercy. And thus far haue we taſted the loue of God, as we might, onely picking out the ſwéete marrowe of that bone which S. Iohn hath caſt vs, for the comfort of our ſoules to feede on: <hi>God ſo loued the world, &amp;c.</hi> In the which ſhorte and ſwéete ſentence duely conſidered and weighed as it is worthy, what find we but ſaluation ſhewing it ſelfe vnto vs in a bright glaſſe, and that (as is aforeſayde) it is a knot knitting vp the whole myſterie of our redemption, wherefore in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereof we haue paſſed to this point,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:51"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8505:51"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8505:52"/>
as that we haue loſed and vndone the ſame, and as grace was giuen, haue layde out the partes thereof to the viewe of the Reader.</p>
               <p>Now that we may gather vp thoſe pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and cloſe the knot againe, let vs ſtand a while and ſée what rockes we haue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, let vs looke backe and view the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull worke of God, declaring his loue to our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: we know therfore what a loſſe we had in Adam being depriued vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly of the fauor of God, for ſo God loued the world, in the firſt foundation that we ſtoode in the ſtate of innocencie, compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the glorious Angels of heauen: we were faſhioned of earthe, but not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered to turne againe into earth: we were made men, but like vnto God: ours matter and ſubſtance was earthly, but our forme and faſhion was heauenly: the patterne whereafter God made vs was his own image, being in ſubiection to god our creator, but reigning as ſouereignes ouer all Gods creatures, bleſſed in oure ſelues in our ſéede walking on a bleſſed earth, enioying at will the fruits &amp; flours of pleaſant paradiſe, that image of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<pb facs="tcp:8505:52"/>
all our ſenſes they were ſette vpon plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure wythout any lothſomeneſſe: what ſounded in the eare, but the ſwéete and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable voyce of Gods bleſſing? Gods bleſſing was alway in our eies, yea what was in oure mouth but Gods bleſſing? Our labor was reſt, our reſte was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, our paines was pleaſure, and oure pleaſure was eternall: we ſweated not, for we had no neede to trauell: we were ignorant of euill, taſting of no corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, free from infirmities, ſtanding in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God without feare, beholding his glorious countenance without ſhame, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health without danger of ſickeneſſe, enioying life without feare of death: the fleſhe and the ſpirite neuer ſtriued, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obeyed the ſoule, and the ſoule ſaued the body, they were knit togyther with a faſt bynding bande, ſo that they might not departe the one from the other: yea then was the body in better caſe than is nowe the ſoule ſeparate from Chryſte, the ſoule was not ſubiecte to death, nor the body in caſe to be corrupted of the duſte: neyther hell nor the graue, nor duſt nor death, no not the feare of them mought touch or
<pb facs="tcp:8505:53"/>
trouble vs, ſo ſtanding as God hadde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. And ſuch was the loue of God, that he gaue all thoſe heauenly commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as a ſtate of inheritance to our firſte father, to him and his heires for euer: O goodly gift of God, wherein the date <hi>is euer and a day,</hi> and nothing betwixt heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth excepted, but only <hi>that the fruit of one tree might not be taſted:</hi> But O fraile fleſh, O lykeriſhe lippes of earthly Adam, that knewe not himſelfe, and conſidered not how mercyful and louing a God he had of his creator, it did not content him to be a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but he would be a God a Gods name, he did not content him to rule and reigne ouer the inſenſible and vnreaſonable, but he woulde ſet his foote as farre forwarde as his Creator, in whoſe handes he was as the brittle claye in the potters fingers. Therefore when that man had ſo giuen ouer the ſeruice of God as raſhly to break his holy commaundement, and to deuour the forbidden fruite: what then myghte the righteous Lorde doe of his iuſtice but plucke downe that preſumptuous ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke? but ſet his face with furie againſt rebellious man? but hate him, but curſe
<pb facs="tcp:8505:53"/>
him, and cleane caſte him off, as one that deſpiſed his goodneſſe, vnworthy of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and vtterly to be reiected as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of the Serpent, the ſlaue of ſinne, and a méete helhounde for the Deuill? Verily ſo are we without Chryſte curſed creatures, children of diſobedience, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of perdition, euer rebelling againſte the ryghteous God, ſeruing the fleſhe with his appetites, gyuen ouer to concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, the loſt ſonnes of the loſt father, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing heauenly, but altogyther earthly, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the worlde and the preſent life, as a ſhadowe whoſe ende is eternall darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and as a courſe to runne headlong to Hell, being nothing but naked ſoules, aſhamed to ſtande in the ſight of God, no not the beſt of all, were we as holy as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dauid, but muſt be faine to ſaye after hym, <hi>I haue ſinned,</hi> as whoſe righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are but rotten ragges all to beſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the foule blurre of ſinne, whoſe hope is deſperation, whoſe life is without lyght, and whoſe deſert is death. So are we falne, and our féete ſerueth vs not to get vp againe, we are taken pryſoners in captiuitie with the Deuill, and we are
<pb facs="tcp:8505:54"/>
not ſo ryche as to redéeme our ſelues: for our deſertes are but ſuch, that when we haue reckened all that we can doe, yet are we but vnprofitable ſeruants: but who is he that commeth ſo neere perfection, as to performe that duetie, to ſet his brother equall in loue wyth himſelfe, and to ſette God before himſelfe, and that in al times, all places, and al reſpectes? and who then is he that dare aduenture the tryall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to ſtande to the extremitie of the lawe? S. Paule hath tryed that way, and gyueth vs a faire warning, as that, the lawe ſtoppeth euery mouth, no fleſh ſhall be founde righteous by that rule. Let vs then caſt aſide thoſe figge leaues, whyche can not hide our nakedneſſe, that is the deſerts of the fleſhe, the deedes of the law, for this waye we maye be ſure to méete with that curſe: <hi>Curſed is he that abydeth not in all that is written in the lawe:</hi> Let vs not make ſo litle of the loue of Chriſt, and ſo much euacuate his croſſe, as to iuſtifie our ſelues by any lawe: for if righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be by the law,<note place="margin">Galath. 2.</note> then Chriſt died with out a cauſe. Neyther will excuſes ſerue to ſaluation, for then ſhoulde the Serpent
<pb facs="tcp:8505:54"/>
haue bene curſed alone, as vpon whome all the blame was layde: but if the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſeduce and be followed, if the Deuill tempt and be not withſtoode, both Adam &amp; Eue, man and woman, they muſt néeds drinke of the cup of Gods curſe. This for the knowledge of oure ſelues, what the world is which God ſo loueth, and ſo ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before vs our reward by iuſtice, the terrible torments &amp; intollerable flames of hel fire, with the bitter byting worm that neuer dyeth, whiche Satan threatneth, leading vs forward faſt fettered with the chaine of ſinne, what might we do but lye ſweating in the myſerable &amp; pitiful pangs of deſperation? what comfort might we finde one in another, but teares and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſorowes &amp; ſighes, crying and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, wéeping and wayling, groning and gnaſhing of téeth? But the merciful God, the louing Lorde, when we ſtoode at this point in manner at defiance with God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſawe that al fleſh had corrupted his way, although he knew the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mans heart to be euil euen from his youth, and ſaw that we alwayes bare a ſtyffe ſtomacke agaynſt him, and his
<pb facs="tcp:8505:55"/>
holy will, yet hath he not vtterly caſt vs of, but bleſſed be his name for euer, he hath ſhewed vs a glad and chearefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, hée taketh pitie vpon vs, it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him we ſhould deſerue his wrath, but it woulde more grieue him that we ſhould die the deſerued death. Wherefore he hath ſhewed vs marueylous kindeneſſe, and more mercie than when we ſtoode firſt in his fauour, yea more mercie, I will not ſay than man might deſerue, but more than we coulde deuyſe to aſke. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, he hath opened vnto vs all his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and endleſſe riches of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, chooſing out as it were the beſt iewell of all hys ſtore and ſtocke, euen that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pearle, his owne glorie, in whome is all his delight, his onely begotten, hys beſt beloued ſonne,<note place="margin">Collo. 2.</note> in whome dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the Godheade bodily, in whome are hid all the treaſures of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, who is the verie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Image of the inuiſible God, him he hath not ſpared to make our Meſſias, and to ſende vs a ſauiour, to rayſe vs from that foule fall of our firſt father, to regenerate and make vs a new, to conquer the world,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:55"/>
to ſlay the ſéede of the ſerpent, and ſée that we ſhoulde not periſh, but liue and reigne with him in his kingdome euerlaſtingly: and how Chriſt hath approued himſelfe a ſauioure, and how he perſited that knotty worke of our redemption, and made all ſure that it might not periſh, what he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered before he ſaid, <hi>(it is finiſhed)</hi> we haue ſéene ſome ſhewe thereof: but O that we could conſider it worthily, and weigh it in a iuſt ballance: then ſhould our harts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly waxe hote with the feruent loue of God, ſo maruellouſly declared in hys ſonne our ſauioure, bearing this in mind alwayes, that whatſoeuer he ſuffered, he ſuffered for vs: hauing ſtill that voice of our Sauiour ringing in our eares, and freſh in our harts: the zeale of thy houſe hath conſumed me: Chriſte was ſicke of that conſumption, euen of zeale, to make vs an holy houſe to his father: and what ſoeuer was done by Chriſte on the earth, let vs recken altogyther vppon the ende whereof he himſelfe proteſteth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> the ſonne of man came to ſaue that whyche was loſt, and whatſoeuer was layde vppon him, let vs recken that ours by ryghte,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:56"/>
and that we deſerued a thouſande folde more than ſo:<note place="margin">Eſay. 52.</note> for we alas like giddy ſhéepe haue gone aſtray, we haue turned euery one of vs his owne way, we were oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with burthen of ſinne, but by him we are eaſed and refreſhed, for he hathe layde vpon him the iniquitie of vs all, that are come vnto him with our heauy lode: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he hath borne our infirmities and caried our ſorrowes, he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was broken for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities, the chaſtizement of our peace was vpon him, and with hys ſtripes we are healed: he came downe from the high heauens to raiſe vs that were faſt ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to the déepe darke hell: he refuſed not to take vpon him the burthen of our fleſh, that we might by him be quickened in the ſpirit: he liued amongſt vs men, that we by him might liue with God: he ſuffered ſuche euill entreatie at that Foxe Herods handes, leaſt we might be a portion for Foxes, and a pray for woolues: he follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed that thankleſſe office of preaching, that we myghte not periſh but liue by hys worde: for though the deuill ſay nay, yet Chriſt ſayth truely, that man liueth by
<pb facs="tcp:8505:56"/>
euery worde procéeding out of the mouth of God, and therefore rather than hée woulde leaue vs vnprouided of that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary foode whiche he brought from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, he tooke well a woorth the miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of the wicked blaſphemers: That we might call on him as a Sauioure, he ſuffered himſelfe to be called a Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, a ſinner, a ſurfetter: and for our ſouls h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it was, that he wrought ſo many a miracle by the meanes of one body cured viſibly, ſauing a thouſand ſoules by inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible operation of faith: ſo Chriſt himſelfe ſaith: vnleſſe you ſée ſignes and wonders, you will not beléeue: therefore to lay that ſalue to our ſore alſo, he profeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Phiſition and a Surgion, nothing diſdaining the company of ſuch as were in miſerie, and deſpiſed of men: he ſhut not his eyes to the blinde: he came to the lame that coulde not come to him, he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on the Lepres, he viſited the ſicke, he wepte with the ſorrowfull, he lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wyth Lazarus, fewer times bidden to feaſtes, than he was founde at burialls. But this is to be accounted the leaſt part of al the paines &amp; ſorowes of our ſauiour.
<pb facs="tcp:8505:57"/>
The cup, the curſed cup of his croſſe, what hart is ſo harde that may conſider that without great admiration of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? with howe bitter temptations did he take the taſt therof before his hour came? with what heauineſſe of hart did he vtter his complainte vnto his diſciples? and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his father when he ſweated that bloudy water? let vs heare then our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure himſelfe vttering his complaints, by the mouth of the Prophets? Thus ſaith one:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.</note> he is deſpiſed and reiected of men, he is a man full of ſorrowes, and hath expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of infirmities, we hidde our faces from him, we eſtéemed him not: thys we knowe howe it was accompliſhed, in that the hanghtie high Prieſtes and proude Phariſies, regarded not, but vtterly dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned our Sauiour: by another Prophet he ſaith: he that eateth bread with me, lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp his héele againſt me: This we ſaw performed by ſaucy Iudas, who when he had dipped with our Sauiour in his diſh, ſtreight after gote him out and made vp his bloudy bargaine, and as Chriſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned his diſciples, deliuered the ſonne of man into the handes of ſinners: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:8505:57"/>
Scripture is:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.</note> he is broughte as a ſhéepe before hys ſhéerer, that openeth not his mouth: ſo was he brought before Annas, Cayphas, Herode and Pylate, of whome he heard euill wordes ynough to moue his pacience, but it was vnmoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, therefore he gaue them the hearing, and anſwered their quarrelling queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with humble ſilence: for pacience and ſilence they were two of the ſharpeſt weapons he mainteyneth his kingdome withall. Another ſaying of our Sauioure is this: I gaue my backe vnto the ſmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and my chéekes vnto the nippers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 50.</note> I hid not my face from ſhame and ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: how that was tried true we know, when our Sauiour was ſo roughly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of Souldiers vnder Pilate, now layd on with fiſtes, now ſmitten with rods: and how ſhamefully he was beſpetted,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.</note> the Euangeliſt dothe moſt faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: and howe he helde hys backe to the tormenters, what backbyting he had as well by euill entreatie, as miſreportes, thereof Pylats bitter ſcurge may be for witneſſe ſufficiente:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.</note> another Scripture ſaythe: he is broughte as a ſhéepe to the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:58"/>
ſlaughter: in ſuche manner did our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our goe out of Ieruſalem to the place of hys execution called <hi>Caluaria,</hi> where hee was offered vp an innocent lambe, and ſlayne as a ſacrifice with bloude for our offences: And ſo dothe the Prophete crie in the perſon of Chriſte, pouring out hys complaintes, and declaring the terrible pangs that he had on hys Croſſe: I am (ſaythe he) become a worme and not a man,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.</note> a ſhame of men, and the contempt of the people, all they that ſée me, haue me in deriſion, they make a mow at me, and nod the head, ſaying, he truſted in the Lorde, let hym deliuer hym, let hym ſaue hym ſéeing hée loueth hym: agayne hée ſaythe: I am lyke water poured out, and all my bones are out of ioynt, mine hart is lyke waxe, it is moulten in the midſt of my bowells, my ſtrength is dried vp lyke a potſherde, my tongue cleaueth to my iawes, and thou haſt brought me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the duſt of deathe, for doggs haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me, and the aſſembly of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hathe encloſed me, they pierced my handes and my féete, they gaue me gall in my meate, and in my thirſt they gaue
<pb facs="tcp:8505:58"/>
me vineger to drinke: they parted my garmentes amongſt them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.</note> and caſt lottes vpon my veſture: rebuke hathe broken my hart, and I am full of heauineſſe, and I looked for ſome to haue pitie on me, but there was none, and for comfort, but I founde none: Theſe were the ſighes and ſobbes vttered of the Prophet to be verified of our Sauioure, whiles he was in that terrible horror and dreadfull an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of ſoule, as he lay like a lambe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the croſſe, and moſt bitterly blée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to deathe: for ſo farre dyd he ſubmit himſelfe in the cauſe of our redemption, that he is made the moſt perfect patterne of all pacience: ſo did the loue of God work in him, that he was conſumed euen of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry zeale to hys houſe: ſo was he turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and tormented, bruſed and broken, racked and rent into péeces for euill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing ſeruauntes, for our diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hée performed the vttermoſt poynt of obedience, as Sainte Paule ſaythe, he was obedient to the death, the deathe of the croſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:59"/>
               <head>The fourtenth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶The ſweeteneſse of Gods loue, fealt by a true and liuely fayth.</head>
               <p>THis was the price paid for our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this was the purchaſe of our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, euen the moſt precious bloudſhéeding of the only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſon of God: ſo hath the merciful Lord ſtretched his loue towards the world in Chriſt, euen to the top of the croſſe, and ſo to the bowels of the earth, the bottome of the graue, from whence he is riſen to the right hand of the father ther to reigne, vntill he haue troden his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies cleane vnder his féete. Now we to whome belonged nothing but ſhame and reproch, may fréely glory without all ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of vanitie: we that in ourſelues had no cauſe but to lament, haue nowe good leaue to reioice, reioicing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, now may we withoute all feare triumph ouer our enimies with that ſure Souldier of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 15.</note> &amp; ſay: O death wher is thy ſting? O graue where is thy victorie? May we now ſtay ourſelues, but to fal in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of gods infinite mercie, and ſay with the Apoſtle: O the déepeneſſe of the riches
<pb facs="tcp:8505:59"/>
of God: with the Prophet, O Lorde, what is man that thou viſiteſt him? or what is the ſonne of man that thou ſo regardeſt him?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15.</note> No man can haue greater loue than to giue his life for hys friendes. What then mighte we now aſke more at Gods hands?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 10.</note> what péece of loue is there nowe left which god hath not fully beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs? for Chriſt is that good ſhephearde which layth downe his life for his ſhéepe: O Lord what is man that thou ſhouldeſt ſo regard him? O that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would conſider this loue of God which S. Iohn maketh ſo much of, that he repeateth it again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: In this (ſaith he) appeared the loue of God toward vs, bycauſe God ſente hys only begotten ſonne into the world,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Epist.</hi> 4.</note> that we might liue through him. And agayne, herein is loue (ſaith he) not that we loued him, but that he loued vs, and hath ſente hys ſonne to be a reconciliation for our ſinnes. Let this ſentence be well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The loue of God is a well contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the water of life, whoſe operation is reconciliation, whoſe riuers are righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, whoſe ſtreames wipe awaye the ſands of ſinne, whoſe little drops re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh
<pb facs="tcp:8505:60"/>
the hote hart of man, flaming and boyling with the ſmoking fire of Gods furie: and beſides this, it is a fountaine not forced but fréely ſpringing of it ſelfe: ſo ſaythe S. Iohn: it is not a reward for a deſert, it is not loue for loue, one for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, but it is loue for hatred, mercy without merite, fauoure for falſhoode, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for obſtinacie, pardon for rebellion, the payment of honoure for the debte of ſhame, bringing hope for deſperation, and lyfe vnlooked for in place of deſerued death: thus dothe S. Iohn lay foorth the loue of GOD before vs, as it were ſtill harping on thys one ſtring, <hi>(God ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the vvorlde)</hi> and on thys playeth S. Paule alſo, not without great pleaſure, &amp; in ſuch ſort that I thinke where it entreth the eare, it may not but muche moue the hart: for firſt he putteth the Epheſians in mind of their old eſtate, in what caſe they ſtoode before they were called to the grace of the goſpell, that they ſo knowing them ſelues, might the better knowe God &amp; hys goodneſſe towardes them: <hi>ye were</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>dead in treſpaſſes and in ſinnes,</hi> yée in time paſt walked according to the courſe
<pb facs="tcp:8505:60"/>
of the world, and after the Prince that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the aire, euen the ſpirite that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the children of diſobedience: and here ioyning himſelfe and his fellowes with the Epheſians, <hi>among whome we alſo had our conuerſation in times paſt in the luſts of our fleſh, and were by nature,</hi> what were they? <hi>the children of wrath as well as others.</hi> Such were they, ſuch children are we all as we are the children of Adam, withoute the loue and the beloued ſon of God. But now Chriſt is come, what news bringeth he? <hi>But God</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>which is rich in mercie through his greate loue wherewith he loued vs, euen when we were deade by ſinnes, hath quickened vs togither in Chriſte, by whoſe grace ye are ſaued, and hathe ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs vp togither and made vs ſit togither in the heauenly places in Chriſt Ieſus</hi> O what is man that God ſhould ſo loue him, as thus to poure vpon vs the whole ſtore and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his mercy, and to beſtow vpon vs his chiefe iewell, his only begotten ſonne, and by him to exalt vs eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the déepe hel to the high heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? Surely God hathe maruellouſly ſhewed hys gracious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon the children of men, but in this
<pb facs="tcp:8505:61"/>
that he ſo loued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world as to giue vs hys ſon, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the heauens, the earth, ſo dothe this farre ſurmount al the proſperity that any people, al the felicitie that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at any time hath euer enioyed: it was much that God bleſſed Abraham ſo as to gyue him the deaw of heauen, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fat of the earth, enriching him with great ſtore of treaſure and flocks of cattell: but what was this to the bleſſed ſéede that bleſſeth all nations? and Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al his royaltie, what was he but a lilie in the garden, and a floure in the fielde, but that he was aſſured of that promiſe made vnto hys father, that vnto Dauid ſhuld be rayſed a righteous branch and a king ſhould reigne and ſit vpon hys ſeate, whome we ſhould call the Lord our righteouſneſſe? God as he had before the comming of our Meſſias, choſen to hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Iſraelites a peculiar people, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e he tendered as the huſbandman his vine, ſo his hande wrought maruellouſly wyth them, and beſtowed innumerable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits vpon them: goodly and glorious were the frutes and floures that God cauſed to flouriſh in that vine, but if we be braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches well graffed in the true vine, then
<pb facs="tcp:8505:61"/>
may Englande well compare with Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. For whatſoeuer they receiued other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we haue receiued as fully and wyth as large conditions in Chriſt the ſonne of God: they had but the figure more than we, we haue the body and ſubſtance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as well as they: theirs was the ſhales, but we haue parte in the kirnell: they had the ſhadow aboue vs, but we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the true ſunne of righteouſneſſe equall with them: there was a greate iubilie no doubt among the Iſraelites, when that voice was firſte heard on the mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai: I haue ſéene the affliction of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whiche is in Egypt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.</note> and I am come downe to deliuer them: but what was this to the ioyfull tidings brought of the Aungell? <hi>vnto you is borne in the Citie of Dauid a Sauioure,</hi> and by another Aungell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math,</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall ſaue his people from their ſinnes.</hi> Herein was loue as Sainte Iohn ſayth: farre in deede mighte that people ſéeme to be in the fauoure of God, that he did ſo mightily by his ſeruante Moſes deliuer them out of the hands of hardharted Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao and that cruell countrie of Egypte: But O Lorde what is man that thou ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8505:62"/>
loueſt him, as by the croſſe of thy Chriſte, to plucke him out of the bloudy clammes of that roring and rauening Lion Satan, and to ſaue vs from that hote burning E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypte the fiery furnace of hell? God made Moyſes a maruell and a mirroure before his people: but he neuer gaue hym thys commendation: Thys is my beloued ſonne.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.</note> Naye to which of the Angels ſaid he at any time: Thou arte my ſonne, this daye begat I thee? yet thys beloued ſonne whome the father maketh ſo much of, is made our Moſes to fulfill the lawe, and our Meſſias to fill vs full of grace: he hathe broughte vs out of all bondage,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.</note> it is he that hath led captiuitie captiue: and nowe are we free in déede when the ſonne hathe made vs frée: Dauid refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth hymſelfe maruellouſly wyth the memorie of thoſe benefytes of GOD whyche hée beſtowed vpon hys people when they were nowe paſſing from Egypt toward the promiſed land: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he vttereth ſuch ſayings in hys pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and ſongs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.</note> recording therin the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God: he deuided the Sea and led them through: In the daye alſo he led
<pb facs="tcp:8505:62"/>
them with the cloude. This was theyr Baptiſme vnder Moyſes, as Sainte Paule ſaythe: Nowe if we be baptiſed in Chriſte Ieſus with water and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: then haue we drowned Pharao in the floud, and haue buried vp Sathan ſafe in the Sea: then are we couered and clothed with the true cloude, ſo that the heate of hell may not hurt vs: ſo ſaithe S. Paule:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galath.</hi> 3.</note> All ye that are baptiſed into Chriſt haue put on Chriſt, and ſo ſaithe S. Iohn of the water falling fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that cloude:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Epist.</hi> 2.</note> The bloud of Ieſus Chriſte cleanſeth vs from all ſinne: Dauid goeth forward and ſaith: as he led them in the daye tyme with a cloud, ſo he did all the nighte with a light of fire.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.</note> This was a great token that God was with them: but this was but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of him that ſaythe: I am the light of the world, he that followeth me ſhall not walke in darkneſſe, but ſhall haue the lighte of life: This is the lyght,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.</note> that is the lyfe of men, this is the light that ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the darkeneſſe: here hathe the Gentile gotten as muche as the Iewe: for this is the true light that lighteth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man that commeth into the world.
<pb facs="tcp:8505:63"/>
Againe ſaithe Dauid, for the glory of the Iewe he claue the rocke in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and gaue them drinke as of the great depthes:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 10</note> but Paule ſaithe alſo, for the comforte of the Gentile, the rocke was Chriſte: for out of the rocke rent on the croſſe guſhed out that plentifull <hi>aqua vitae</hi> whyche ſerueth to ſatiſfie the thirſt of euery ſoule: that is it, which ſhall waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all our vncleanneſſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.</note> That although our ſins were as crimſin, they ſhall now be made white as ſnowe: though they were red lyke Scarlet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.</note> they ſhall be as wooll: though they be ruſty for ſinne, as thoſe that haue lyen among pottes, yet ſhall we be as the wings of a Doue that is couered with ſiluer, and whoſe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are lyke vnto the yellowe golde. Wherefore without this water, was that nothing in compariſon, but as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſayth in hys reaſoning wyth the woman of Samaria concerning Iacobs well:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.</note> Whoſoeuer ſhall drinke of thys water ſhall thirſt agayne, but who ſo drinketh of the water which I ſhall gyue him ſhall neuer thirſt agayne, and it ſhall be vnto him a well of water ſpringing vp
<pb facs="tcp:8505:63"/>
into eternall lyfe. Another maruellous benefite of God doth Dauid glory in, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: God opened the dores of heauen, and rayned downe Manna vpon them for to eate, and gaue them of the Wheat of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſo man did eate Aungels foode: this was a ſure token of Gods ſingular loue towardes them: but this was but a ſhadowe to that which Chriſte bringeth with him: for ſo he himſelfe maketh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon: I am the breade of life: your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did eate Manna in the wilderneſſe and are deade:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> I am the liuing bread whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che came downe from heauen: if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eate of this breade he ſhall liue for euer: finally that God by the hande of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant Ioſua conducted his people and ſette them ſafe in the poſſeſſion of Canaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that lande ſo long looked for, ſo commended, that it ſhould flow with milke and hony, therein did he ſhew himſelfe, as a mightie ſo a moſt mercyfull God:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 1.</note> but bleſſed be the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che according to his abundant mercy, hath begotten vs againe vnto a liuely hope, by the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt from the deade, to an inheritance immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb facs="tcp:8505:64"/>
and vndefiled, and that fadeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. This is that eternal poſſeſſion whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Chriſt hath purchaſed for vs with the price of his precious bloude, <hi>euen the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and glorious kingdome of his heauenly father.</hi> O bleſſed Bées that may be ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as to ſwarme about Chriſt, and to ſuck the ſwéete hony flowing from the floures of that Canaan: verily there is heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hony, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as the eye hath not ſéen, the eare hath not heard, neyther yet hath euer entred into the heart of man: that is it which God hath prouided for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued: it was vndoubtedly a great loſſe which we had in Adam. But thankes be vnto God we haue founde more in Chriſt than we enioyed before.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> So ſaint Paule maketh conference of both eſtates: for if by the offence of one, death reigned thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh one, much more ſhall they which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the aboundance of grace and of the gifte of righteouſneſſe reigne in life thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh one, that is Ieſus Chriſte. O Lorde what is man that thou ſhouldeſt be ſo mindfull of him? But herein is loue, that Chriſte hath purchaſed vs a newe Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, &amp; is gone to prouide vs a kingdome,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:64"/>
euen of his own kingdome doth he make vs fellow heires, he rayſeth vs togyther with him to the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly places, and with his crowne of thornes he hath gotten vs the crowne of glorie that euer floriſheth and neuer fadeth: although we eate not the fruite of the trée of the knowledge of good and badde, yet may we be ſure to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king peare (I meane) <hi>to periſh:</hi> althogh we meete not with the trée of life which ſtood in the old Paradiſe, yet in the high pillar of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Almightie God, comming to Chriſte his heauenly table, we ſhal not miſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthy fruit <hi>to haue life euerlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>The fiftenth Chapter.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶The aſſurance of ſuch as take holde of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie freely offred in Christe.</head>
               <p>THus haue we looked on and ouerloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the beautifull worke of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our regeneration in Chryſte Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lorde, we haue aſſayed to drawe vp that which was layd abrode: now ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to knit vp the knot and to make a through ſtyche, let vs caſt aſyde all ſelfe loue, and ſticke onely to the loue of the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:65"/>
liuing God, the true fountaine and wel of the water of life: bearing ſtill in mynde the ſaying of S. Iohn: <hi>God ſo loueth the worlde,</hi>) and that he ſaithe, herein is loue not that we loued him, and that oure loue is but a fruite of the roote: for ſo he ſaith:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Epiſt</hi> 4.</note> therefore we loue him bicauſe he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs firſt: let vs therefore begin to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken there where we haue to fetch all good things, whether it be loue, light or life, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from that firſt fountaine whiche S. Iohn hath ſo ſet ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>och before vs, ſaying: <hi>he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs firſt,</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what he ſaith <hi>in whom God ſheweth all his mercie: (without me ye can do nothing:)</hi> and what he ſaith to them that take parte with him: <hi>to you nothing ſhall be vnpoſsible:</hi> and aboue all things let vs conſider the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder which that deede of gifte paſſeth: God hath giuen his ſonne, <hi>that whoſo beleueth in him,</hi> he ſhould haue loue and life with God: So doth God drawe vs vnto Chriſte, as he pronounced by his Prophet:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28.</note> he that beléeueth on him ſhall not be aſhamed. And Chriſte calleth vs vnto him:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> come vnto me al ye that are heauy laden: how may we come but by the foote of faith?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> for whom he calleth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he
<pb facs="tcp:8505:65"/>
iuſtifieth: and we being iuſtified by fayth haue peace towardes God through oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, by whome alſo we haue acceſſe through faythe (ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) vnto this grace wherein we ſtand:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.</note> for want of fayth it was that Chriſte was not receiued of his owne, but the beloued beleeuers they receiued him: to them he gaue the power to be the ſonnes of God, they are knit faſt to Chriſte, they are the body, and he is the heade, they are frée by him, they are frends in one houſe, felowes in one inheritance, and ſonnes of one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our Lorde Ieſus O how happy are we if we haue faithe: for then are we choſen, we are called, we are iuſtified, we are glorified: God is on our ſide: who may ſtand againſt vs? what ſhall we now dout to obtaine at Gods hands? for he that ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not his ſonne, but gaue him for vs al: howe ſhall he not with him giue vs all things alſo? we are Gods choſen: who ſhall lay any thing to our charge? Chriſt is dead, he is ryſen: euen he to whome all iudgement is committed, he maketh ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſute and continuall requeſt, he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for vs: who ſhal then condemne vs?
<pb facs="tcp:8505:66"/>
who ſhal ſeparate vs now from the loue of Chryſt? Shall tribulation or anguiſhe, or perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſſe, or perill, or ſword? in all theſe things (ſayth S. Paule) we are more than conquerors through him that loued vs: And vpon this is he ſo bold that he ſayth: I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that neyther death nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſente, nor things to come, nor heigth, nor depth, nor any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lorde.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 15.</note> O let vs ſet this example of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Paule before vs, let vs holde faſt the loue of God with him: howe came he by that bolde and mightie ſpirite? by the grace of God I am that I am (ſayth he) &amp; againe: we haue boldneſſe and entrance by fayth in him, that is, in Chriſt Ieſus: wherefore his exhortation ſhall be moſte neceſſarie at al tymes: watch ye (ſaith he) ſtand faſt in the faith, quit you like men &amp; be ſtrong, let vs put on the armor of God, let vs not feare to enter the fielde hauing Chriſt our Captaine, &amp; aboue al, let vs be ſure to take with vs the ſhielde of faithe:
<pb facs="tcp:8505:66"/>
that hath S. Iohns warrant, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we may conquer the world as Chriſt hath done: and S. Paules, that therewith we maye quenche the fierie dartes of the wicked: and S. Peters alſo, that with the mightie force of faith we may mouſell vp the bloudy mouth of that roring Lyon, ſo we being armed and fortified with fayth, we maye walke free without all feare: now we may defie the ſerpent &amp; his ſéede with all their ſubtiltie: let the Deuil now rore and rage, let him fret, let him fume, &amp; fome, Chriſt is on our ſide, in whome the Prince of this worlde hath naught to do: let him as he dare fling vpon vs his fierie darts, the ſhield of faith ſhall ſoone quench them: let him caſt his blockes and ſet his trees againſte vs, yet by fayth we ſhall ſoone remoue and rent them by the rootes: let him throw mountaines vpon vs, let the gates of hell be ſette open vpon vs, yet what is that can preuayle againſte vs? what may ſeparat vs from the loue God? Chriſt is riſen and we ſhall not be kepte down: for in him as S. Paule ſaith:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 2.</note> we are raiſed vp togither through the faith of the operation of God, whiche rayſed him fro
<pb facs="tcp:8505:67"/>
the dead: wherefore I exhort ſuch as loue their life and like the loue of God, and ſay againe with S. Paule that which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſaid to much, <hi>ſtand faſt in the faith of Chriſt:</hi> let vs heare his warning while it may profite vs: This is the condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayth Chriſte) that light is come into the world,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> and men loued darkneſſe more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> light: And againe on the contrarie part, he calleth vs vnto him on this wiſe: While ye haue light, beléeue on the light that ye may be the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of light: let vs beware therefore, and as we would be loth to loſe our part in that ioyfull tydings of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, <hi>vnto you is borne a Sauiour:</hi> ſo let vs take that warning of Chriſt, <hi>beleeue in the light:</hi> vpon this point ſtandeth the whole cauſe of our redemption: God he hath ſent light into the world, &amp; that light is life to the beléeuer: betwixt beléeuing &amp; not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, there now lieth the whole matter a bléeding: if we beléeue not, then no doubt but we bléede to death: for Chriſt is come, and this is he that ſhould come, &amp; we muſt not loke for any other: he is dead, and he dyed once for all, he offered one ſacrifice, and that once for all: let vs therefore now
<pb facs="tcp:8505:67"/>
or neuer beware that Chriſt be welcome vnto vs: that he denie vs not before his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that we be welcome vnto him at his next comming. For he ſhall come the ſeconde tyme, not as before, to ſaue that which was loſt, but to ſitte in his glorious throne, and to iudge who is ſaued and who is loſt. Then ſhall he vſe his left hande as well as his right hande, he ſhall ſift the good corne from the chaffe: the one part ſhall be gathered into the barne, but the other ſhall be moſte terribly burned with vnquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fire: and it is fayth that maketh and marreth in this matter, that is the knyſe wherewith Chriſt ſhall cut the partes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder: if we beléeue we liue, if we beléeue not, we liue not: for it is decréed that Chriſt ſhall deale thoſe two diſhes: <hi>to periſh, and to haue life euerlaſting:</hi> And he hath alreadie made the deuiſion, and ſhall as certainly diſtribute it. And this is thy portion O vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie infidell: Chriſt biddeth thée depart from him, for thou haſt not receyued him, thou haſt refuſed the loue of God offered in Chriſt, and therefore muſt thou take thy part with the Diuell and his fellowes: thou ſhalt periſh and not haue life euerlaſting:
<pb facs="tcp:8505:68"/>
but bleſſed are you ye faythfull beléeuers, you haue the right hand, Chriſt biddeth you welcome, you are the beloued of God, you haue not bene aſhamed to receyue Chriſt on the earth, and he ſhall receyue you in the high heauens, you ſhall poſſeſſe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious kingdome prepared for the choſen of God, <hi>you ſhall not periſh, but haue life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi> The which God graunt vs of the loue wherwith he ſo loueth the world for his only begotten ſonnes ſake. God be bleſſed for euer Amen.</p>
               <byline>By M.A.K.</byline>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>The yeare of our Lorde. 1562.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:8505:68"/>
            <head>A godly aduiſe touching Mariage</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orſhipfull, as I am not vnmindfull, ſo I deſire by theſe not to ſeeme vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thoſe rewards, not ſmall in my purſe, which you haue heretofore of your liberalitie diuerſe times beſtowed on me. The which my purpoſe, is not here to recompence, as Courtiers thinke ſufficient to rewarde other mens good workes with their fayre words: but yet I thought it good maner firſt to make this curteſie, before I entered any further matter with you: leaſt I ſhould ſeeme ſtill to begge, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to bring, or elſe that my bringing might ſéeme nothing elſe but a coloured begging, euen as the ſubtill fawning Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell ofte tymes fetcheth hys Mayſters gloue in hope to chaunge it for a better morſell. Wherefore vnderſtand you, that this procéedeth not of any ſuche purpoſe, as eyther to picke any thanke for an vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued good turne, for therein you are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hande with me, eyther to quite you
<pb facs="tcp:8505:69"/>
with like meaſure as you haue met vnto me, for that is alſo aboue my reache: but onely I wiſh you to accept this as a pledge of a gratefull minde, confeſſing vnto you a debt, and yet deſiring a pardon of payment. And ſuche is the pledge whiche I haue to commende vnto you, ſurely without diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, no better than of that whiche is growne in mine owne ground, no farre fet thing, neyther dearely bought, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not méete for you, eſpecially if you bée very Ladie fine, no greater than that came out of my penne, not more precious than may be kept and caried in a poore péece of paper, of no further forme and faſhion, than mine owne handes could frame, mine owne ſimple witte might worke. The fine cooke men dight the rude morſell with ſome conceyte of their cunning, but I haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sugar to grace my diſhe withall, but as I haue ſayde. Wherefore as you ſée, ſo ſhall you taſte: as you like the qualities, ſo accept my preſent. Whereas therefore your gentleneſſe is ſuche that it deſerueth great thankfulneſſe, and otherwiſe moued if you had not ſette me vp this marke, I thought it my part (if you ſhould take it in
<pb facs="tcp:8505:69"/>
good part) not to ſpare penne, paper nor paines at this preſent in writing vnto you: and although it were more meete for me to treate tryſles than myſteries, things of naught &amp; little force, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> matters of weight and great importance: yet conſidering your perſon, whoſe caſe requireth euen in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced tryfles to ſéeke a grauitie, and I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loth that loſt labour ſhoulde run with loſt time, (for loſt time I account loſt la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds) haue bethought my ſelfe to deuiſe ſome matter that happily might quite your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor for reading, and not be altogither fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in wit, ſo that altogither my wordes might not ſéeme as waſted winde, and I might be ſomewhat botter occupied than as one that did naught elſe but tell the clockes and watch the ſunne howe he ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doweth the diall. Conſidering therefore the ſtate of your life, the caſe wherein you now ſtande: that is, towards me and the world my ſiſter, a woman once a wife, nowe a widow, and therefore hauing of God leaue and libertie by mariage to become a wyfe againe: for when the huſbande is dead, the woman may lawfully betake hir ſelf vnto another. This your caſe I reckened ſo far
<pb facs="tcp:8505:70"/>
to be mine, that I might not like a careleſſe ſtraunger ſtand dumbe, but as a well wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing brother open my mouth, &amp; vtter my mind vnto you, not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I mind to perſuade or diſſuade mariage with you, for therin you may beſt be your own iudge, for you know beſt where you ſhooe wringeth you: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther need you any counſeller to bid you cut where it wringeth you: But whereas you know it lawfull, if you ſhall thinke expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent alſo, that of a widow you becom a wife, then ought you to take good aduiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t how you beſtow your ſelfe, leaſt you both ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and marre your ſelfe in one day, and of an happie widowe become an vnhappie wife. For I neede not to ſeeke to ſhew you the daungers that ſuche leapt into, that in this matter raſhly leapt before they wiſely looked: bicauſe on the one ſide others haue had experience in you, and on the contrary you haue ſufficient experience in other, which may lead you through the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof euen as ſtreight as a line: and therefore I will not counſell you as néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to aduiſement, but rather commende you that you haue hitherto ſtand ſo ſtayed, with ſuch aduiſed deliberation. Onelye
<pb facs="tcp:8505:70"/>
this poynt I finde in you, whiche néedeth a knot, as to conſider howe you might doe moſt aduiſedly, what matche were moſt méete for you to be made, that repentance follow not: to what marke you ought to direct your counſell, aduiſement, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, that the ſucceſſe might aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere your hope, that is, that it myght turne to your continual comfort, and to the glory of God. This verily I wote well is a caſe of ſuch importance to conſider, and hath ſo many hard knots to worke on, that it were more fitte for gray heares, ſage wits, &amp; depe diuines to take in hande, than for my ſimplicitie to aduenture. I thinke you haue read what M. the Emperor ſayd in the like caſe: I am of opinion, that if all the wiſe men were molten togither in a fornace, they could not giue one good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to make a mariage, what counſell then of likelihoode may you looke to haue at my handes, if a wiſe man, if many wiſe men, if all the wiſe be not wiſe ynough in anie poynt well to aduertiſe you in this behalfe? Wherefore I will aſke no pardon of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, whereof I truſt there ſhall be no ſuſpition betwixt brother and ſiſter. But
<pb facs="tcp:8505:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:72"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:72"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:73"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:73"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this deſire, you would rather weigh the wil than the wit, which by me here ſhal be ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed: and if I (as of likelyhoode) ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoote my ſelfe by any kinde of follie, yet let ſuch wiſdome reſt in you, that you make not that ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; common, which betwixt vs is priuate and priuie. Therefore to enter my purpoſe, bicauſe that of many, yet muſt one ioyne but with one, and bicauſe where one is to be choſen, it is good to ſée whiche and all if it might be. I will be ſo bolde as to ſende you foure ſuche ſuters as may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent vnto you all the reſt that may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen hereafter to come. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider all by foure, trie foure and truſt one. Therefore I ſée thrée markes generally whereat you may ſhoote out your game, and whiche are to be conſidered in man. The inward minde of the man, the outwarde perſonage and the ſtate wherein he ſtandeth of things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning to the worlde. By this rule I will ſeuer and ſingle out the ſortes of men, that after the deuiſion you may with leſſe doubt make your choyſe. And firſt to begin with the worſt: There are men that liue ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther well, nor welthily, being in a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſtate both toward God and the world,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>
paſt hope, and paſt ſhame: But we maye ſet theſe aſide, as we finde them, ſo let vs leaue them, for I know as they are naught worthie, ſo you will not haue to doe wyth them. None of thoſe I thinke will come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in the name of a ſuiter. The next man is not ſo wiſe, nor ſo wel fauoured as welthie, not ſo curteous as couetous, not ſo manered as monied, and he hauing hope through his wealth peraduenture will at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt you. For what caſe is deſperate in the worlde to ſuch as fortune laugheth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as one ſayth: wherevnto doth not the religious thirſt of golde enforce the hearts of men? This man you may ſoone eſpie, where his treaſure is, there is hys heart: euen ſuch kind of wowing you ſhall haue of him as Satan vſed to our Sauior: if thou wilt fall downe and worſhip me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 4.</note> I will giue you (ſayth he) all theſe: you ſhall be maiſtreſſe of ſo many ſhepe, ſo many ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, thus muche money ſhall be yours as mine owne. So harpeth he vpon his halfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penie. But let vs ſet him aſide a while, and bring an other in place, as ſuch a one, that is handſome of perſonage, eyther as they ſay, a tall gentleman, or a proper man, wel
<pb facs="tcp:8505:75"/>
borne, graced with ſome courtly behauior, well ſpoken, a pretie naturall witte, and graced with other ſuch qualities of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and yet peraduenture vertue hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken little or no roote in him, he worſhippeth God at leyſure, and hath ſome ciuill godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in him, and a religion he hath that he vſeth as the Market ſerueth, and thus doth he recken his game: I ſée not (ſayth he to himſelfe) why I ſhoulde diſpayre, I ſée not but I am worthie of as good as ſhee is, I come of as good an houſe as ſhée, mine aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceters were all worſhipfull, and ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable: I doubt not the miſlyking of my behauiour, for I haue not beene ſo euill brought vp but I knowe howe to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne a gentlewoman, I ſhall ſée well y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough too, that my demeanor be curteous and courtly, as for my countenance, my perſonage, I force not who beholde it. So to himſelfe he ſayth, when to you he ſhall commende himſelfe with ſuch modeſtie, as to ſay, he is not diſfigured nor maymed: and that he cannot of ſhame ſay him ſelfe, ſome other fréende ſhall ſet out in play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner termes, his fréendes peraduenture not yours, will ſo blaze his armes, as
<pb facs="tcp:8505:75"/>
thoughe he ſhoulde ſell him vnto you, as though ye ſhoulde take him at his worde, beſetting him with theſe &amp; the like floures: if you reſpect the perſonage of a man, if you refuſe him, yée ſhall not bée ſo matched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, marke him and viewe him well, ſée what deformitie you may finde in him: is there any part of him out of ioynt, or out of ſquare? Marke what a ioly complexion he hath, ſee whether ye may eſpy any wart, any blemiſh in his viſage: conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be not a very gentleman in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, and forget not hys qualityes how commendable they are, his actiuitie, his merie conceytes, his pretie practiſes: ſée howe cleanly and trimme he is in his apparell, howe ſkilfull and neate he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his horſe, his hawkes, his houndes: his exerciſe alſo be vſeth, is gentleman like, abroade he vſeth his bowe, within doores he can ſing to his lute, and ſo he hath wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped cleane the outſide of the cup. As for learning hée hath ynoughe for a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Here peraduenture that wyſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be wiſely alledged. <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 7. Be not too wiſe: if he haue a good witte in déede, then ſhall there be great compaſſes
<pb facs="tcp:8505:76"/>
of compariſons ſet. If he be but meane in that reſpect, then yet he is no foole, no natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: if he be peraduenture ſomwhat ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in fame, as for the familiaritie, you ſhall haue that iſſue ſtreight ſtopped wyth ſome playſter of excuſe: if it be not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, then is it falſe and forged, no man is able to charge him ſo, the beſt are moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to corruption, the fineſt cloth may bée ſooneſt ſtayned, the honeſteſt man may bée ſooneſt ſlaundered. And if it be not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, yet it ſhall be excuſed, as that thoſe are but toyes and pranckes that runne in common courſe among yong men, or elſe you muſt conſider that we are all ſinners, and there is Scripture ynoughe to proue this: There is not one good, no not one, we haue all gone aſtray like ſhéepe, no man is good but God, and ſuch the like. Wherefore a man is not to be reiected, but to be borne withall in ſuch things, for as much as wee are al full of imperfections and infirmities. And ſo if there appeare any good gift it ſhall be ſet out as it were a ſunning to beholde. But if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re be any ſuſpition of vice, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe any want or defect, that ſhall ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be let ſlippe with ſilence, or elſe the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:76"/>
broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> péeces ſhall be glued togither in ſome ſort, that which is vnſéemely or vnſightly ſhall haue a better colour ſet on it wyth ſome gloſing tale: the want of wit ſhall be ſupplied with abundance of wealth, euill maners with much money, if his life be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected you muſt looke in his face, for with ſome women the pleaſing perſonage ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth for it ſelfe, and alſo for vertue: and good qualities is for learning in a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. If the quiuer be well furniſhed, if it be well in the ſtable, in the mue, the kenel, it doth not ſo muche force what is in the houſe, the chamber and the ſtudie. Suche verily is the table talke amongſt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils the gentlemen, ſuch boltes ſhootes ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and ſuiters frendes, and with ſuche traynes ſome women are entrapped, with ſuche winleſſes ſome are dryuen into the net. But I truſt your eyeſight ſerueth you better, than to be dimmed with ſuche myſtes, or dazed with ſuch ſhort ſunſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. In the degrée of myſuters, the third remayneth, whome if you by the eye iudge, that diſcerneth no further than the face, and if you weigh the worth of your mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with weightes of ſiluer, this man ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:8505:77"/>
ſoone be put out of countenance and hope, he ſhall ſoone be counteruayled and weyed downe to the grounde, as who may ſing Peters ſong: Siluer and Golde haue I little or none, he can not number hys landes, his leaſes, hys farmes and his tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: not of great liuing, but of good life: he hath a liuing, but competent, not aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, not flowing with full ſtreame: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture no knight, yet a plaine gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, not verie well borne, but verie well brought vp, not worſhipfull, but worſhippe worthie, not of great eſtimation, but of ſingular honeſtie, not ſo long trayned in the Court as conuerſant in the ſchoole, hys landes are not ſo great as his learning, his cheſt not ſo ſtored with money, but hys heade and minde poſſeſſed and furniſhed with the truſtie treaſure of truth, and the ineſtimable wealth of wiſedome: hys de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes to others are not comparable, but hys demeanour aboue others commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and amiable countenaunce, but yet a manly viſage, a face in whiche appeareth more grace than fauour, more grauitie than beautie, his tongue ſpéeding wordes no faſter than they maye ſéeme well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:77"/>
hauing his mouth in his heart, and not his heart in his mouth: not ſo well friended of men as fauoured of God, hys bodie not ſo handſome of making as hys ſoule well faſhioned &amp; framed to godward, his leg not ſo clean as his life without ſpot, his hande not ſo white to ſée, as his heart ſure to truſt: not high of ſtature, yet his wit not ſhort, his body not ſo ſtreight as his conſcience vpright, not ſo braue in his appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell as graue in his behauiour, not curious &amp; neate, but honeſt and clenly, not ſo wel faced as well liued, I meane not ſo well attyred in the outwarde man as clothed in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde man. Theſe are me thinkes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées of men to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered in our purpoſe: for I can recken no other markes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto women direct their eyes and thought. Shée that reſteth vpon theſe thrée firſt, thoſe which they call the giftes of fortune, the outward goodes as welth and ſubſtance whiche they poſſeſſe, their place and ſtate, their parents and friends concerning wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and eſtimation, and in the man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the goodes of the minde, wherein you may reſpect ſhortly life and learning and wit: then the perſonage of the man, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:8505:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his making and proportion, his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, his forme and fauour, and alſo hys yeares: and although theſe good giftes and graces do not enioy one the other, but that ſometymes in one perſon diuerſe of them may make their habitation: for the better conference of them to ſeuer them into dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe perſons, I woulde you could diſcerne them apart in déede: then ſhould you be in leſſe daunger of deceyte: there are to be founde I thinke, if we ſéeke farre, in whom vertue, fortune and fauor haue made a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: and ſuch a one, if my prayer might be heard you ſhoulde ſoone attaine. But ſuche ſtarres ſhoote not often, ſuch birdes flie ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome abrode: but if there happen any ſuch wherevpon your conſideration ſhall ſtand, my counſell is that you follow the example of the Phiſition, who to knowe the whole ſtate of a man openeth and cutteth him vp, and deuideth him into partes, and thereby groweth into a greater knowledge: ſo I wiſh you to make an anotomie of him that you haue in hande, make no confuſion of wealth, witte, bodie and ſoule, life and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: For ſo you may ſoone deceyue your ſelfe. In one man therefore conſider thrée,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the which you ought to chooſe but one, leaſt perhaps you miſtake your righte marke &amp; léeſe your game: leaſt in ſtead of a man, ye find but the ſhadow of a man: referre your ſelfe to the patterne of thoſe perſons which I haue rudely deſcribed vnto you: compare vnto them, and thoſe betwixt themſelues. Wherfore to enter the compariſon, if you aſke my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: The Poets to lay a foundation of a further inuention, fayned there were thrée ſhée Gods in contention for their beautie, who did moſt excell: <hi>Iuno,</hi> who had the diſpoſition of honor and dignitie, <hi>Pallas</hi> at whoſe pleaſure were al gifts of wiſedome, &amp; <hi>Venus</hi> the Lady of loue. To end this ſtrife, it pleaſed <hi>Iupiter</hi> and other gods, to refer the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hereof to one <hi>Paris,</hi> a ſhepehearde, conueying to him a golde apple with this inſcription: Let it be giue to the faireſt. The foreſayd Gods preſented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues before this their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed iudge, and offred euery one their rewarde to haue ſentence on their ſide: <hi>Iuno</hi> would make him the higheſt: <hi>Pallas</hi> the wiſeſt: &amp; <hi>Venus</hi> a huſband of the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb facs="tcp:8505:79"/>
               <hi>Venus</hi> here preuailed, ſhe was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced faireſt. <hi>Paris</hi> had his rewarde, that was the beautiful <hi>Helena,</hi> who they ſay, was the cauſe and deſtruction of the Troians. Nowe if your mariage ſtoode vpon the gift and deliuerie of an apple, I truſt you could not play <hi>Paris</hi> part, that <hi>Venus</hi> ſhould vanquiſh you. Wherefore my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rather you encline to <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> for ſome reward of wit: than either to <hi>Iuno</hi> for hir honor, or <hi>Venus</hi> for pleaſure. And beſides theſe, there is one that by right hath greater intereſt in the apple than any of the other, although ſhe ſtriue not ſo much for the matter, I meane the Ladie Vertue. Wherefore if ſhee come in place, wyth-holde not your hand from hir for feare of the other, if ſhe offer not hir ſelfe at the fyrſte, yet be not raſhe or haſtie, but call vnto God that he maye ſend hir vnto you, and he no doubt, as his eares are always open vnto the prayers of the faithful, ſhal bring hir eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> home to you, and ſhe, I think, is for your purpoſe, to hir as you ought, deliuer vp your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple if you intende to giue it to the faireſt,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the beſt &amp; the moſt worthy. Wherfore conſider wel my laſt pourtred perſon, of whom although I haue not ſet ſo faire a colour, yet if he were to be ſold, I would hold as deareſt: as who, althoughe he be not formed of the fineſt faſhion, yet is he made of the pureſt mettal: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture <hi>Iuno</hi> may ieſt at, <hi>Venus</hi> haue lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to vaunt of, &amp; <hi>Plutus</hi> whome they call the God of riches paſſeth not on: yet if vertue may preuaile, you ſhall be his, &amp; vertue ſhal be yours, yea <hi>Pallas</hi> alſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on his part. Wherfore I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel you as you wold giue the apple vnto vertue, ſo giue your wedding ring to be worn of the vertuous. For if it be ſo, as the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher truly diſputeth of frendſhip, that it can not conſiſt but betwixte the good: how ſlender a mariage wil that be, wher vertue knitteth not the knot? where ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie is not called to counſel, and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is not bid to the bridall? I thinke there needeth no farre fette examples in this matter, ſeeing you haue experience ſo néere you: you know what the ſon of Syrach ſayth: bleſſed is that man that
<pb facs="tcp:8505:80"/>
hath a vertuous wife, for the number of his yeares ſhall be double. You I thinke being vertuouſlye diſpoſed, entende to make an happy huſband: ſee then that he do as much for you as you for him: wher as you ſhal make him happy, foreſée that he for want of vertue turn not the courſe of your ſtate: whereas you ſhall double his dayes, take héede that he cut not off yours by the middle. <hi>Eccleſiaſtes. 26.</hi> You haue ſome good floures growing, take héede they be not ouergrowne &amp; choked with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil wéedes that he ſhal bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: you are, thanks be to god, diſpoſed to godlineſſe, match not with the contrarie diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for then ſhal you be as the yoke of oxen that draweth diuers wayes. Vice and vertue were yet neuer friends, it cauſed hatred in brethren, as in Cain &amp; Abel, Eſau &amp; Iacob: howe can the wolfe and the Lamb agrée? no more can the vngodly with the righteous. He that toucheth pitch ſhall be defiled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Think not then that the vertuous and the vicious may make a good mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: Can you ſet fire and water togither,
<pb facs="tcp:8505:80"/>
but that they ſhall ſtir and ſtriue for the maiſtrie, and eche to conſume the other? Stand therefore, make no haſt for feare of the worſte: it is better to looke long than to leape lightly: rake vp the aſhes thorowly, and turne them to and fro, that you be ſure ther remain no ſpark of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vice, or at the leaſte, leaue as little as you may, and ſwéepe as clean as you can. Therefore marke wel, I wiſh, what condition S. Paule ſetteth, when he gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you your licence to marrie <hi>1. Cor. 7.</hi> The wife is bounde by the law, as long as hir huſband liueth, but if hir huſband be dead, ſhe is at libertie to marie onely in the Lord. Weigh well that reſtraint of your libertie, or rather a ſure ſtaye of your libertie, leaſt by abuſe you turne that libertie into a bondage. For vnleſſe you haue God before your eyes, you ſhal chaunge your libertie into a ſtreyght bondage: wheras you ſeeke comfort, you ſhall finde a curſe, whereas you hope for eaſe and reſt, you ſhall enter into diſeaſe and trouble. Aboue all therefore haue a ſpecial and a ſtedfaſt eye vpon this rule:
<pb facs="tcp:8505:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
That you marie in the Lorde. He made the firſte mariage that euer was made, and I dout not but he made the firſt that you made: and if he make the ſeconde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, then ſhall you be ſure neuer to repent you of your bargaine. He did inſtitute mariage as a thing moſt holy, to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and to the comfort of man: Sée ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that you in your caſe be voyde of all fleſhly affection as neare as you maye, that you prophane not that which is holy to your owne diſcomfort, and the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of God. Chriſt you know was preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at a mariage in Cana, where beſides his preſence, he honored it with his firſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, as that he turned water into wine. I pray you make Cothring as like Cana as you can, let Chriſt be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with you: I meane, to guide your ſpirite with his holy ſpirit, turne not his miracle, make not, I meane, water of wine, but let that which God hath inſtituted to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, be godly handled of you to his glory. Whereas Matrimonie is honorable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſte all men, prouide that it turne not to your ſhame and confuſion, as you
<pb facs="tcp:8505:81"/>
ſée in ſome: I néede not here (as it were to long) particularly to giue you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, to rehearſe ſhe vertues to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, &amp; the vices to be deteſted in men. But ſhortly, as our Sauiour anſwered, thou knoweſt the commaundementes, doe this and thou ſhalte liue: So I, you know the commaundementes, mete the length of their féete, by that meaſure ſhal you well perceiue whether his ſhoe will ſerue your foote: yet one thing in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe I muſt adde, not of miſtruſt, but to make a double knotte of a ſingle, or a treble of a double: for the ſurer the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the warier the wiſer. Be wiſe then and beware, that you put not your head vnder the girdle of the vngodly, neyther ſo burden your ſelfe as to beare the yoke with an Infidell. For then it maye not ſéeme you kept S. Paule his rule. As to marrie in the Lord, for that is his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>6.</hi> For what mariage maye rightuouſneſſe make with vnrightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? light with darkneſſe, Chriſt with Beliall, the vnfayned children with the faythleſſe Infidell? For here beſide the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:82"/>
daunger of diſcorde and bodyly trouble thereof enſuing, there is alſo apparant perill that may pearce the ſoule. For ſo ſayth the Lord to his people Iſraell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their ioyning with forein nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Deut. 7.</hi> Thou ſhalt make no coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with them, neither ſhalt thou make mariages with them, neyther giue thy daughter vnto his ſonne, nor take his daughter vnto thy ſonne, for they wyll cauſe thy ſonne to turne away from me, and to ſerue other Gods: Then will the wrath of the Lorde waxe whote againſt you and deſtroy thée ſodenly: You are no Iſraelite, here might be ſayd, how then? yet a Chriſtian I trow, and by fayth the daughter of Abraham. Then this muſt you recken to be written for your lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. There are no Heathites, no Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, no Cananites to be feared: yet are many in our dayes bothe faythleſſe and godleſſe, as the obſtinate Papiſte &amp; dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealing Goſpeller, in whom there is no leſſe daunger of deceite: and although the perſons be not one, yet litle differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſeemeth to be in the cauſe. For firſt mark
<pb facs="tcp:8505:82"/>
the reaſon, and then apply it. The mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of a Cananite was forbidden the Iſraelite, for feare leſt he ſhould be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen from the true worſhippe of the true God of Iſraell: and do we not ſée in experience that the wicked wife cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth ſuch men as we iudge ſometime moſte vpright in lyfe and ſtedfaſt in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truthe. And howe muche more danger is there leaſt the vnbelée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and wicked man alter the good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the honeſt woman into his owne nature, ſéeing that to hym ſhe is ſubiect, as the body to the head? ye muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie be one in fleſhe with him whome ye ſhall chooſe: foreſée therefore by wiſdome that hys religion be one with yours, ſée that you change not your maners with your name: preſume not of your ſelf her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, you are not wiſer than Salomon, yet as in the <hi>.9.</hi> of the <hi>.1.</hi> of the kings, his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was ſo bewitched by the means of thoſe forein wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he matched in mariage, that he became a fond Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; ſo fel into the hands of god. Of this example I truſt you will take ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:8505:83"/>
warning, ſo that herein I néede not make any moe wordes: vnleſſe you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to me or any other to you, the place of S. Paul <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>7.</hi> The vnbeleeuing huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>band is ſanctified by the wife, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beléeuing wife is ſanctified by the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band If we marke the purpoſe of Saint Paule, the anſwer ſhall not be hard: The verſe next afore dothe conteine his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, which is that the beleeuing woman already maried to the vnbeléeuing man, ſhould not vſe his infidelitie as an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to departe from him: the words are: The woman which hathe an huſbande whiche beleeueth not, if he be content to dwell with hir, let hir not forſake hym: and the other he ioyneth as a reaſon to confirme this ſentence, ſo that that place ſerueth to this, that if you and your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band were firſt both of you vnbeleeuers, afterward it pleaſed God to call you to the knowledge of thys truthe, your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band continuing in his infidelitie, or if nowe beeing grounded, you ſhoulde ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the mariage of an Infidell, you ought not yet for the hope of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb facs="tcp:8505:83"/>
to ſéeke a ſeparation For as you ſhould do ill to take on the yoke of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell, ſo ſhoulde you do worſe to ſhake it off withoute ſome iuſter cauſe: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that be not a ſufficiente cauſe to breake the knot that is knit, whereas is hope of ſanctification, yet is it iuſt and neceſſarye wherefore to refraine mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. For the mariage of an vngodly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell I graunt is a mariage, &amp; not light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be diſſolued: but yet an vngodlye mariage, and that whiche lacketh ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, whiche is eaſie to gather eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame wordes of S. Paule alleaged. Wherefore as if your head were faſt in the yoke I would counſell you to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue for the hope of ſanctification, that you might win your huſbande: ſo nowe ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding frée, tempt not God, preſume not, match not with any that you knowe to be out of the houſholde of faythe for feare of corruption, leaſt you leeſe your ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you winne an other. Thus I haue ſpoken hitherto for my laſt wower, who pleadeth honeſtie, vertue and godlineſſe, and who I doubt not ſhall ſpéede, bicauſe
<pb facs="tcp:8505:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that God is on his ſide. Here if ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of me, whether I woulde haue you ſo preciſe as only to regarde the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie and vertue, withoute any further reſpect. Truely (although peraduenture I ſhall ſeeme too ſpirituall in this poynt) that if you had your eye fully fixed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marke, without wauering other wayes, no doubt but God would proſper you the better, for as muche as he ſhall thereby haue triall that you depend wholly vpon him and his prouidence, and then ſhall you be leaſt in danger of ſnares And of this, that it ought ſo to be, we may take a warning of the maner that God vſed in the firſt mariage making in the. <hi>2.</hi> of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis, as whileſt he was prouiding for Adam the woman that ſhuld be his wife and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, he cauſed an heauie ſléepe to fall vpon the man, and whileſt he was a ſléepe, he tooke out that ribbe wherof he framed the woman. So verely I would thinke that God did moſt worke with you, if you layde Adam a ſleepe, I meane, if you remoued all carnall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and worldly reſpectes whyche
<pb facs="tcp:8505:84"/>
procéede as earthly from Adam, whyle that this bargaine were a driuing. This I know is farre wide from worldly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: but this way you ſhall go néereſt to make a mariage of Paradice, and ſo ſhall you ſéeme moſte to marrie in the Lord. And if you may not abide ſo ſtraite binding, yet ſwarue as litle as you may: if thys be not your whole building, yet at the leaſt let it be your chiefe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if thys be your grounde, haue no doubt but there will growe and folowe other good followers. So then I thinke you ſhall gather a good ſumme if you caſt your accomptes in this wiſe: if vertue come alone, ſhe is not to be refuſed: if ſhe come with the companye of ſuche as the world eſtéemeth, not as a ſeruant but as a maiſtreſſe, which is hard and ſeldome, ſhe is alſo to be imbraced. But yet if you ſtande on this poynt, you are in greater danger to ſlide: for vertue clothed is not ſo ſure to truſt as if it be naked &amp; bare. Then a little vertue excéeding in one, maye not be ſupplied with great ſtore, and abundance of other gifts and goodes
<pb facs="tcp:8505:85"/>
in an other: for we muſt in our doings firſt ſeeke the kingdome of heauen, as for other things, after them ſeeke the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, if they be ſought with care, euen when we thinke vs neareſt we are often furtheſt off, and ſhoote to ſhort. If we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the thing deſired, yet we lacke the fruition, as when we wanted the thing. If we enioy it, yet the ſpace is ſhorte. But if they come as vnbidden gueſtes, then are they moſt welcome: yea if we ſeeke them not, the promiſe is, they ſhall be caſt vnto vs: and if they be caſt, then come they in their kinde. Nowe then to ſpeake ſomewhat of other reſpects ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, you may reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the ſuiter whom I commended vnto you, I did ſo qualifie, that as I would not haue him godleſſe, ſo I wiſh him not to be witleſſe: for that I recken a moſt honeſt reſpect, ſo that you diſcerne the true wiſdom from the falſe, ſo that the ſimplicitie of the doue ioyne not with the wilineſſe of the ſerpent: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall this hinder my honeſt &amp; godly wower in his ſuite, but rather further. For as fooles are fortunate, ſo the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb facs="tcp:8505:85"/>
commonly haue leſſe want of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The feare of the Lord is wiſdom. Iob. <hi>28.</hi> Chryſt is the wiſdome of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: therefore if you make accompt of true wiſdome, in this behalfe you ſhal be beſt ſped in the true Chriſtian: and by this I néede not to make compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the godly and the wiſe, ſo that you vſe your wiſdome to diſcerne and iudge aright of wiſdome, for as much as the right wiſdome the righteous hathe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned. Only if the compariſon ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the wiſe and the welthy or hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, let Salomon be your counſellour here. Prouer. <hi>8.</hi> Wiſdome is better than precious ſtones, and al pleaſures are not to be compared vnto hir: and Prouer. <hi>16.</hi> How much better is it to get wiſedome than golde, and to get vnderſtanding is more to be deſired than ſiluer. And thus the Preacher maketh compariſon. cap. <hi>7.</hi> Wiſdome is good with an inheritance, and excellent to them that ſée the ſame: for a man ſhall reſt in the ſhadowe of wiſdome, and in the ſhadowe of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. But the excellencie of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:8505:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of wiſedome gyueth life to the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors thereof.</p>
            <p>Nowe if the righteous and the riche ſtande in compariſon, yet I truſt my poore ſpirited ſuter ſhall not be outfaced, you ſitting as iudge: and ſuche I truſt ſhall be your ſentence, as was <hi>Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocles</hi> anſwere (a Captayne among the Grecians, to thys queſtion) whether a man ſhould beſtow his daughter vpon a good poore man, or vpon a riche man not ſo honeſt? his aunſwere was (as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſheweth, <hi>lib. 2. officiorum</hi>) I rather lyke the man who lacketh mony, than money which wanteth a man. So little thought he that riches and ſubſtance did make a matter of mariage, that ſhe ſéemed not to him to marrie for anye regarde of the man, that hath ſuch reſpect of riches: and that ſhe that maryed not an honeſt man, did ſcarſe marie a man. Some in déede haue their fanſie ſo ledde as thoughe moneye made men: But let this be your Poeſie rather, when you make your mariage: Manners makes man. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſaying of the Prophet. Pſal. <hi>37.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8505:86"/>
and Prou. <hi>16.</hi> A ſmall thing that the iuſt man hathe, is better than great riches of the vngodly, wicked and mightie. There is a good péece of counſel in the <hi>.13.</hi> of Eccleſiaſticus, concerning thoſe with whome we may not win familiaritie, for he ſayth: Burthen not thy ſelfe aboue thy power whileſt thou liueſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany not with one that is mightier and richer than thy ſelfe: for howe agrée the Kettle and the earthen pot togither? For if the one be ſmitten againſt the other, it ſhall be broken. Wherefore in thys be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half an equalitie were a goodly propertie. That would take away the occaſion of ſuch quarrels and complaints as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall matches (we ſée) lay one in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers diſh, which choaking morſels you know are not eaſie to digeſt. I wiſh you welth and riches, for I knowe they are the good gifts of God. But I feare leaſt vertue will be ouer whelmed where ſuch flouds breake out. He that will tarrie for the company of a rich man to go to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, it will be long or he come there. For his way is as ſtreite as the eye of a
<pb facs="tcp:8505:87"/>
néedle, and he himſelfe as huge as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel Eccleſiaſticus maketh a maruaile of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rich vpright man <hi>.20.</hi> or <hi>.2.</hi> Chap. Haue not this mind with you (ſiſter) as to ſéeke a rich mariage For then you miſſe of the right marke of mariage ordeyned for your comforte: there lyeth not the way leading to reſt and quietneſſe <hi>.6.</hi> Timo. For they that will be rich, fall into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and ſnares, and into many foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyſome luſtes whiche drowne men in perdition and deſtruction, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate that ſaying with your ſelfe: the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of money is the roote of al euil. Take heede that that roote ouergrow not other good floures: but hearken vnto the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that our Sauioure pronounceth: Woe be vnto you that are rich, for you haue receiued your conſolation. Luke <hi>.6.</hi> Theſe therefore be the boundes that S. Paule appointeth vs: If we haue, ſayth he, foode and rayment, let vs therwith be content. Truly herein conſiſteth not true riches to poſſeſſe this earthly treaſure, the meate of Mothes, and the bayte of theeues: But ſuche as my commended
<pb facs="tcp:8505:87"/>
ſuter poſſeſſeth, if you may be partaker thereof, then maye you ſay: my lot is fallen to me on a faire grounde, and that you haue a goodlye heritage. Godlineſſe (ſaith the Apoſtle) is greate gaine, if a man be content with that he hath: euen that is it which my ſuter bringeth, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe with contentation. Wherefore then ſhoulde you deſire the mariage of the rich? you ſée it bringeth no reſt: you ſée godlineſſe is the true riches. Do you ſeeke to ſtabliſh vnto you and yours an inheritance? Hearken then what the Prophete ſayth. Pſal <hi>.37.</hi> The euill doers ſhall be cut off, and they that wayt vpon the Lord, they ſhall inherite the land. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game, the meeke men ſhall poſſeſſe the earth. And againe, the Lord knoweth the dayes of vpright men, &amp; their inheritance ſhall be perpetuall. Do you ſeeke a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance &amp; perpetuitie in things? Iames ſayth, as when the ſun riſeth with heate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the graſſe withereth &amp; his floure fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth away, &amp; the beautie of the faſhion of it periſheth: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſhal the rich man fade away in all his wayes. But the iuſt they
<pb facs="tcp:8505:88"/>
floriſh like the palme trée, they are like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bay trée, euen gréene &amp; freſh like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Pro <hi>.12.</hi> The roote of the righteous ſhal not be moued. Do you deſire to haue ſuch a head as may beſt defend you from iniuries and oppreſſions: who is of more might than the righteous? Dauid ſayth. Pſal. <hi>34.</hi> The angell of the Lord pitcheth rounde about them that feare him &amp; deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth them. And againe: the eares of the lord are open vnto their praiers, and his eares are open vnto their crie, yea he ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth their bones that none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, he numbreth their heares that none of them be loſt. Do you feare peril or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie? of the righteous thus ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Pſa. <hi>37.</hi> They ſhal not be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the perillous time, and in the days of famine they ſhall haue inough. You will ſay, for my ſelfe I can hold my ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, but my childrens caſe moueth me. Harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how Dauid ſpeaketh of his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. Pſal. <hi>37.</hi> I haue bin yong and now am old, yet I ſaw neuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, nor his ſéede begging their bread. Doubtleſſe GOD ſhall prouyde for
<pb facs="tcp:8505:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you and yours ſufficientlye and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, if you caſte awaye all ſuche worldly reſpectes, and muche more than otherwiſe. Nowe I thinke theſe ſhall ſuffice to vnderſet and ſtaye you vp that you fall not on this ſide. The next care concerneth my ſecond ſuter, that he take you not with the bayte of beautie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by manye wiſe women and men haue bin deceyued, and with a ſhorte pleaſure haue purchaſed long and deſperate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. This cauſed Salomon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit follie <hi>.11.</hi> of the <hi>1.</hi> Kings. This cooled ſhe mightie Sampſons courage. Iud. <hi>16.</hi> Did not the beautie of <hi>Bethſeba</hi> ſo rauiſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes of holy Dauid, that he committed with hir moſte abhominable adulterie, and made him alſo guiltie of bloudſhed? So it is written <hi>.11.</hi> of <hi>.2.</hi> Samuel. He ſaw a woman waſhing hir ſelfe, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was very beautifull to looke vpon. You might abuſe theſe examples to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as to ſaye: Theſe men were notable for ſtrength, for wiſedome, for godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: maruaile not then (mighte you ſaye) though I be ouercome in that caſe.
<pb facs="tcp:8505:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Not ſo ſiſter, but thys conſider in theſe examples, that if ſuch of ſo excellent gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces haue bene ledde awaye with theſe traynes, you haue hereby a faire war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to beware, and to be very circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in ſo ſubtill a pointe and ſo daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a caſe: if you giue place to ſuch fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies that they ouercome reaſon, you may ſoone ſlip into thoſe inconueniences that you ſee in the examples of others, you may plucke the houſe on your head as Sampſon dyd. As you chooſe your marke ſo goeth your game: as you make your foundation, ſo will your building be: if the one be ſtedfaſt, the other will not lightly ſhake: but if the one be not ſurely grounded, a little blaſt marreth much work: ſurely the handſome perſon of man is not of long continuaunce. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, it is ſubiect to corruption by innumerable meanes. Wherfore if your mariage hang vpon that knot, a little force will breake it, a little laboure will vndoe it, and of it ſelfe it will decay and weare away. If this fanſie be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leader of your loue, you follow a blinde guide, you
<pb facs="tcp:8505:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
may ſoone ſlide and wander out of your right waye. Many an vnſauery wéede beareth a faire bloſſome: ſo vnder a faire face, there lieth hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many a foule fault, and with ſounde looke often is couered the hollow heart, all hatred. (A liuelye example in Abſolon. <hi>14.</hi> Sam. <hi>2.</hi>) I haue read an hiſtorie of one <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> a noble man of Rome, matched with a wife called <hi>Papiria,</hi> both for birth and beautie (to iudge) worthye ſuche an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande. Howbeit he diuorced hir: and when hir friends entreated for hir, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding of him what ſhoulde be the cauſe mouing him ſo to doe, for they ſaw none, ſéeing that ſhe was to behold ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly and modeſt, fayre and fruitefull. Then he for anſwere, thruſteth out hys foote, and ſayth: Beholde, ſee my ſhoe, is it not fayre? is it not newe? yet none of you woteth where it wringeth me. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke there was ſome ſecret fault in that woman not to be borne withall, whych was ſo lothſome vnto the huſbande, as hir beautie coulde be pleaſant. Be adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therefore leaſt you finde that your
<pb facs="tcp:8505:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>
handſome huſband haue that, which this man found in his faire wife. If you will not that your ſhoe wring, meaſure hym before you buie, and iudge not of hym by the colour, but meaſure him rather with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in than without, leaſt you wring for it afterwarde. The goodly perſonage with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wiſedome &amp; vertue, what is it better than a painted man? <hi>Plato</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philoſopher in the perſon of <hi>Socrates</hi> thus ſaith to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiades:</hi> He that at any time hath loued <hi>Alcibiades</hi> body, hath not loued <hi>Alcibia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> himſelf: but he that loueth thée, loueth thy minde, <hi>nunc tui corpus amatur. &amp;c.</hi> And the wiſe <hi>Tullie</hi> ſayth: Man is as his mind is, &amp; not that forme &amp; figure whiche may be pointed at with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> finger. For this you vnderſtande that man conſiſteth of two parts, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind endued with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that beareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> image of god: the other as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body which we haue common wyth the brute beaſts. Wherefore Dauid you know, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pareth that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that lacketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding vnto horſe &amp; mule: and I me thinkes, may well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare ſuch luſty lads whoſe commendation is onely on their
<pb facs="tcp:8505:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>
perſonage, and lacketh learning, witte, and honeſtie, vnto <hi>Plato</hi> his Man, as <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogenes</hi> called. When that <hi>Plato</hi> in his ſchoole had defined a man in this wiſe, as to be a lyuing and twofooted creature, made vpright and without any feathers: <hi>Diogenes</hi> thinking that he had not well defined or expreſſed the nature, bycauſe he ſuppreſſed that which was moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to man, and did concerne the mynde and gifte of reaſon, he pluckte me a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon bare and turned him into the ſchole, ſaying: Beholde <hi>Platos</hi> man. Thus is a man if you conſider not his mind, a foole, what is he but an vnfeathered foule? A man without maners, what is he better than a capon without feathers? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you méete any ſuch in your dyſhe, eſtéeme him as you liſt, I haue tolde you the price. Truſt not to ſoone thoſe faire faces, which come like capons vpon ſop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and Sugar. That braue apparell, what is it but Pecockes feathers? the good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexion, the ſtrength of the body, the white hand, the cleane leg, what are theſe, but fading flattering floures? what
<pb facs="tcp:8505:91"/>
but baites to deceiue the fooliſhe fiſhe? all theſe ſerue but to pleaſe the eye, and to ſatiſfie the fantaſie of the fleſhe. Conſider what is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the <hi>.6.</hi> of Geneſis. The ſonnes of God ſawe the daughters of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they were faire, &amp; they toke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of all that they liked. Therefore the Lorde ſayde: my ſpirite ſhall not alway ſtriue with man. &amp;c. Beholde that fleſhly fanſie of mariage, for that they thereby abuſed and polluted the holy ordinaunce of God, is expreſſed there as one of the cauſes that prouoked God ſo to powre out the raine of his wrath, and to deſtroy all fleſhe from the face of the earth. Wherefore in this point I end with the exhortation of S. Iohn <hi>.1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> chap. Loue not the world, neither the thinges that are in the worlde: if any man loue the world, the loue of the father is not in him: for al that is in the worlde, as the luſt of the fleſhe, the luſt of the eyes, and the pryde of life, is not of the father, but is of the worlde: and the world paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and the luſt thereof: but he that ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleth the will of God abydeth for euer.
<pb facs="tcp:8505:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>
By theſe, ſiſter, you may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the true and ſure waye you haue to walke: you haue the bywayes that may cauſe you to wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, in ſome ſort ſtopped vp: you may ſee, if it pleaſe you, the good and the bad, although ſet forthe but in a rude glaſſe, Sing not now <hi>Medeas</hi> ſong, who ſayd: I ſee and allowe the better, but yet I folow the worſe. Giue not <hi>Venus</hi> your apple, but giue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertuous your wedding ring: then ſee how you haue headded your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. And then ſée the bliſſed eſtate you ſtande in, he is yours for better or for worſe, for richer, for poorer, he ſhal be to you an huſband, to your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a father, to your friendes a fauorer, to your eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies a terror, he ſhall willingly beare part of all your blowes and burdens, he ſhall double your proſperitie, he ſhall mourne when you wéepe, he ſhall laugh whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you are glad, his loue is ſure ſealed, euen ioyned by God himſelfe. He is not like the riche of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonne of Syrach ſaith. chap. <hi>13.</hi> if thou be for his profite he vſeth thée, but if thou haue nothing, he will forſake thée. He is not like the light
<pb facs="tcp:8505:92"/>
louer for beauty, of whom the wiſe <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith: He that loueth thée for thy fauor, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that decayeth he wil giue thée ouer. But he ſhal be one with you both body &amp; ſoule, he ſhall walke forth with you here your pilgrimage on earth, and ſhall lead you the way to eternall reſt. He ſhall be bliſſed in all his affaires, if Dauid be a true Prophete. <hi>1.</hi> Pſal. His wife alſo ſhal be bliſſed, he ſhall haue ſéede and bliſſed ſéede: for Pſal. <hi>114.</hi> Bliſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, and delighteth in his commaundements, his ſéede ſhall be mightie vpon earth, the generation of the righteous ſhall be bliſſed: riches and treaſure ſhall be in his houſe, &amp; his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſhall endure foreuer Pſal. <hi>128.</hi> Bliſſed is euery one that feareth the Lorde and walketh in his wayes: when thou eateſt the labors of thy hands thou ſhalt be bliſſed, and it ſhall be well with thée, thy wife ſhal be as the fruitful Vine on the ſides of thy houſe, euen your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands wife ſhal be ſuch a one, if your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band be ſuch a one: &amp; thy childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like the Oliue braunches round about thy table.
<pb facs="tcp:8505:92"/>
This Dauid promiſeth and prophecieth, &amp; confirmeth it againe, ſaying: Loe ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thus ſhall the man be bliſſed (in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying) that man that feareth the Lorde. You will ſaye peraduenture I woulde thinke my ſelfe wel beſtowed vpon ſuch a man: but the craft is in the catching, the doubt is in the obteyning. But goe you forward in your race of vertue, and then you ſhall not goe farre before you méete with a mete match, It is an olde ſaying: The like loueth the like. The ſonne of Syrach ſayth chap. <hi>13.</hi> All fleſhe will reſort to their like, and euery man will kéepe companie with ſuche as he is himſelfe. A vertuous woman ſaith he chap. <hi>26.</hi> is a good portion and a gift to be giuen to ſome iuſt Ioſeph, or ſome true Tobias. You know that euery good gifte commeth from God as the firſte father and founder: yet in this caſe God appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth more euidently to ſtrike the ſtroke to worke as it were immediatly within with his own hand: So ſaith Salomon Prouerb. <hi>19.</hi> Houſe and riches are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce of the fathers, but a prudent
<pb facs="tcp:8505:93"/>
wife commeth of the Lorde. Wherefore although there be good tokens &amp; markes whereby to make your choiſe, as by the fruit to iudge the trée: &amp; as Eccl. ſaith <hi>.27.</hi> The word declareth the hart, the talk is the trial of men: yet bicauſe theſe are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther probable coniectures than ſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations (for fame ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times lieth, the eye deceiueth, the tong diſſembleth) therefore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue caſt the whole &amp; the ſumme, yet God is al in al this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; the onely maker of good mariages. Be frée then from worldly buſineſſe, be cleare from carnall affections, caſt your hope vpon God, depende vpon his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, commit the matter wholly to his hands, reſort &amp; flée to him with oft &amp; ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayer. For that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al other ways be tried, is the plaineſt to ſéeke, the ſureſt to truſt, the redieſt to find for ſuch as ſeek good wiues &amp; good huſbands. You haue a good example in the <hi>.24.</hi> of Geneſis, howe Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proceeded in the mariage of his ſonne Iſaack: you haue there the prayer that the ſeruaunt of Abraham made, to whom this charge was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, howe
<pb facs="tcp:8505:93"/>
he entring his iorney, deſired God to proſper him, &amp; to ſhewe mercy vnto his maſter Abraham, &amp; that God according to his faithful prayer, gaue him a token, wherby he choſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faire vertuous virgin Rebecca For hir parents, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that God wrought with ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, could not deny their goodwil vnto Iſaack, but anſwered: This thing is procéeded of the Lorde, we can not therfore ſay vnto thée neither euil nor good. You haue there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the exerciſe of Iſaack, how he was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in the mean time, while Rebecca was taken out of his rib. Moyſes ſayth: He went out to pray in the field towards the euening, &amp; that Rebecca firſt founde him ſo occupied. This is al, ſiſter, that I haue now to be ſaid: giue your ſelfe ouer wholly vnto God to be your guide. Let your eyes be ſo earneſt bent vpon hym, as they were wont to be vpon your mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe whome you haue heretofore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: then ſhall God, no doubt, giue you as a portion to the righteous, he ſhall ſo ioyne you, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not ſeparat you: Chriſt ſhalbe preſent with you, as at the
<pb facs="tcp:8505:94"/>
mariage of Cana: he ſhall conducte you with his holy ſpirite, he ſhall turne your water into wine, he ſhal make the ſowre ſwéete, and proſper all your affaires: In meane time, while God worketh, be not you idle, but practiſe your ſelf in Iſaacks exerciſe, and God ſhall ſende you an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of his kynde, euen a faithfull ſonne of Abraham, a choſen childe of God. God ſhall ſende his Angell to leade that man vnto your houſe, euen as he brought To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bias vnto Sara at the houſe of hir father Raguel. And as my poore prayer maye helpe, the Lord (I beſéech him) guide you with his holy ſpirite, and prouide you an head for your comfort, graunt you long to liue and euer to loue togither with the encreaſe of your godly chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="Scripture_passages">
            <pb facs="tcp:8505:94"/>
            <head>Certain places of Scripture, touching vngodly matching in Mariage.</head>
            <p n="1">1 THe godly, marying with women of a wicked kinred and Religion for worldly conſiderations, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. Gen. chap. 6. verſe. 1. and .2.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Matching with vnbeléeuers maketh the beléeuing partyes vnreadie to follow Gods calling, and wrappeth them in great daunger of Gods vengeance when it is poured on the wicked: as appeareth Gen. chap. 19. verſe. 14. &amp;. 15.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Abraham tooke an othe of his ſeruant, to take no wife for Iſaac from amongſt the Idolatrous Cananites. Gen chap. 14. verſe .3. and .4.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Iſaac charged his ſonne Iacob, not to marrie a Cananite. Gen. 28. ver. 1 &amp;. 2.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Eſau treſpaſſed in marying wyth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beléeuing women. Gen. chap. 27. verſe. 46. Alſo Gen. 28. verſe. 6. and .9.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Not onely maryages with Infidels, but alſo all other compactes with them are forbidden: neyther may they dwell
<pb facs="tcp:8505:95"/>
in our lande, or any ydolatrous thing be brought into our houſes. Exod. chap. 34. verſe. 12.15. and. 16. Alſo Exod. 23. verſe. 32. and .33. Alſo Deut. chap. 7. verſe. 2.3.4.25. and. 26. The reaſon of this lawe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement is of continuall force, and ſerueth generally for all the children of God, which is: That the beléeuers bée not ſnared by the allurements of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, and drawne to Idolatrie.</p>
            <p n="7">7 By the falſe Prophet Balaams coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the idolatrous women of Moab ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues to the Iſraelites, and ſo ledde them to Idolatrie, as appeareth Numbers chap. 31. verſe. 16. Thoſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men therefore by Moyſes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were put to the ſword: in the ſame chap. verſe. 17.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The matche of Duke Zimrie an Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite, with Princeſſe Cozbie a Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite, with Phincas commendation for ſteaing them both. Numbers chap. 25.</p>
            <p n="9">9 The children of Iſraell did wickedly in marrying with the Canaanites, Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. chap. 3. verſe. 6.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Sampſon reproued by his parentes
<pb facs="tcp:8505:95"/>
(who conſidered the generall lawe of God to the contrarie) for ſéeking a wife amongſt the Philiſtines. Iud. 14. verſe. 3. The inconuenience that inſued of hir betraying his ſecrecie of his riddle to the Philiſtines, in the ſame chap. verſe 17. The yll ſucceſſe of that mariage, in the ſame chap. verſe. 20.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Salomon, the wiſeſt man that euer was, fell away from God to idolatrie by meanes of his outlandiſhe idolatrous wyues, as appeareth firſt of the Kings, chapter. 11.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Iehoram king of Iuda, ſonne of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Iehoſaphat, was a wicked King: the reaſon alſo added: For the daughter of wicked and idolatrous King Achab was his wife. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8. verſe. 18.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Ahaziah king of Iuda, ſonne of Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, a wicked King: the reaſon alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: For he was the ſonne in lawe of the houſe of Achab. His mother alſo was Athaliah the daughter of Omrie King of Iſraell, who was Achabs father. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8. verſe. 26.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Achab king of Iſraell maryed Ieſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel
<pb facs="tcp:8505:96"/>
the king of the Zidonians daughter, in the firſt of the Kings. Chap. 16. verſe. 31. He ſolde himſelfe to ſinne. 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Eſdras reproued the Iſraelites for marying with infidels, as appeareth, Chapter. 9. verſe. 1. and 2. Princes and great perſonages eſpecially there blamed for this fault.</p>
            <p n="16">16 Thoſe vngodly mariages were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued by Eſdras. cap. 10. verſ. 10.9. &amp;. 44.</p>
            <p n="17">17 The ceremonies alſo commaunded, in that ſpeciall permiſſion to the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites of marying an vnbeléeuing woman taken in battell, declare and argue, that it is not lawfull for any of the faythfull to match with an vnbeléeuer, before the vnbeléeuer haue renounced whatſoeuer may be a hinderance to godlineſſe &amp; true religion. Read Deut. chap. 21. verſ. 12. &amp;. 13.</p>
            <p n="18">18 If the huſbande die, the woman is no otherwiſe at libertie to marrie but in the Lorde. 1. Cor. 7. verſe. 39.</p>
            <p n="19">19 We are forbidden to be vnequallye yoked with infidels. 2. Cor. 6. verſe. 14.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Paule ſhewing that he might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully charge the congregation, to whiche
<pb facs="tcp:8505:96"/>
he preached, with a wyfe, reſtrayneth this his libertie both of marying and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo burthening thoſe whome he taught, with this condition: That the wyfe be a ſiſter, that is, a beléeuing woman. 1. Cor. 9. verſe. 5.</p>
            <p n="21">21 In wyues it is required that they feare their huſbandes, that they ſubmit themſelues vnto them as is comely in the Lorde. Epheſ. 5. verſe. 33. and Coloſ. 3. verſe. 18. But no hope of this duetifull feare &amp; ſubmiſſion in an vnbeléeuing wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. For it is commonly ſéene that the vnbeléeuing wife ouerruleth the belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing huſbande, and cauſeth him eyther to make a plaine ſhipwracke of fayth, or ſo cooleth his godly zeale, that he may hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be diſcerned from an infidell.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Parents are commaunded to bring vp their children in inſtruction and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Lord. Epheſ. 6. verſe. 4. and. 1. Tim. 3. verſe. 12. But when the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande and wife be of contrarie religion, this worke of education can in no wiſe be well ordered.</p>
            <p n="23">23 Peter commaundeth wyues to bée
<pb facs="tcp:8505:97"/>
ſuch maner of women as haue hearts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted. Epiſtle. 3. verſe. 4. By whoſe pure conuerſation the vnbeléeuers maye be wonne. In the ſame Chapter. verſe. 1. and. 2. They muſte be faythfull in all things. 1. Tim. 3. verſe. 11.</p>
            <p n="24">24 As vnitie and like affection in all proſperitie and aduerſitie is requyred in all Chriſtians: So eſpecially it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in the godly huſband and godly wyfe, who ought to dwell togither as fellowe heyres of the grace of life, that theyr pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers he not interrupted. 1. Pet. 3. verſe. 7. and. 8. But when a beléeuer is matched with an vnbeléeuer, no hope of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and like affection in prayer to God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:8505:97"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>OMNIA TEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PVS HABENT.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
